[music]
>> Hello, good evening and good day
everybody and welcome to a new history
episode of the Oscar busy show. I hope
you're all doing great. Let me see who
all is there on the live chat and today
I'm going to take questions that you
have asked in the comments. So for the
first couple of hours I'll take as many
questions as possible that I can. The
good ones, the interesting ones that you
all have asked in the comments. There
have been lots of those.
And then if there's time I'll take some
questions maybe from the live chat,
maybe from the super chat. So let's see
who all is there on the live chat. VSVS
2400, Harsh Rai 009, Ishita Khanna,
Akash Spiritual Hacker, MAK4J1U,
Kachru 11,
She She Shir Upadhyay, Adwait Ashwini,
Sumit Agarwal, Harsh Rai 09, Hemi 069,
Sumuk Bhupalam, Nabanita Das, good
evening. Harsh Rai, good evening. Kachru
11, Namaskar. VSVS once again,
Ishita Khanna,
Satellite Geopolitical Dubai, good to
see you, sir. Who else do we have? Al
Janib,
Nirvana Shanks, Konnichiwa, Konnichiwa.
Um Adwait, hello. Pink Cavallier, good
evening, good evening, good to have you,
ma'am. Vishnu Mohanan, Nirvana Shanks
once again, Gravity Kahai, good evening.
In all kinds of colors and fruits, good
to have it.
>> [laughter]
>> Crash and Rise, bonjour, bonsoir, bon
whatever else, monsieur.
Um
Harsh Rai once again, Adwait Ashwini,
Akash Spiritual Hacker, good evening.
Who else do we have? Uh Arya Vashishta,
Isaac Newton is here, good to see you.
Isaac Newton, Nirvana Shanks is on
Kick, is it? On Twitch, on Twitch.
On Twitch, yes.
Um Arya Vashishta, Amrit Singh is here
from Andromeda.
Uh good to have you. Rachna Shringi is
also here and Amisha Mishra is here,
good to see you, hello.
Uh Daksh is also here and everyone else
who's also here.
Uh Vish Shawn is here.
Gajapati Deva, Jai Jagannath from
Odisha. Well, Jai Jagannath back to you.
Okay.
So let's let's get going with the
questions.
Real Vladimir Putin is here. Swami is
here from Jaipur. Are you Singh? Pranam,
Sarji, pranam.
Okay.
And Advocate Samarth Acharya, Namaste,
Namaste.
Ajinkya Pawar is here from after a long
time. Well, good to have you. Good to
have you, Ajinkya Pawar. Good to have
you.
And Rahul Dunakhe also. All right, I
will not be able to greet you all
individually, but let's get going with
the questions. What questions have I
picked this time? Let's take a look.
What are the questions? What's the first
question that we have?
The first question is by Really Now.
The question is, is Islamic or Arabic
architecture actually a thing?
If yes, what is it actually? Because I
see people calling the Taj Mahal Islamic
architecture. Clearly it's made in the
Western Indian style or Marwadi Mewari
fort style, but more like a palace. The
windows, the domes, the courtyards,
everything. Even a kalash at the top,
that's clearly Indian architecture. So
what exactly
is Islamic architecture? What exactly is
Arab architecture? Arabic architecture?
Is that even a thing?
Great question to begin with. All right.
So
first of all,
there are various styles of architecture
that we see in India. Um in the past
1,000 years, you had two periods of
foreign occupation of India. The first
period was the
Turkic occupation of various parts of
India which culminated with the um
greatest extent of the Mughal Empire
under Aurangzeb.
Uh
and once that ends, you had the rise of
the Maratha Empire which liberated the
subcontinent entire almost entirely. And
it then it was
supplanted by the by the British
occupiers of India.
So
for the
for
the majority of the past 1,000 years,
about 700 or so years, there's been a
significant Turkic presence in various
parts of India. Not the entirety of
India at one time, various parts of
India. And because of that there's been
what you could call
the construction of various kinds of
buildings that are said to have an
Islamic style
or an Arabic style or
may mostly Islamic style. The British
architects called it or the British
historians or whoever,
they called it Indo-Saracenic
architecture.
So if you go to the
um
For example, if you go to Mumbai, the
so-called Prince of Wales Museum which
is now called the Chhatrapati Shivaji
Maharaj Sangrahalaya or something like
that.
It is said to be in the Indo-Saracenic
architectural style. So let's take let's
take a look at that. What's What does
the building look like, right? Um
Chhatrapati
Shivaji
Vastu Sangrahalaya.
All right, this thing. Which is the
erstwhile Prince of Wales Museum. So
this style that you see here,
this is a prime example of what some
would consider or some would classify as
the Indo-Saracenic architectural style.
Which has, according to them, elements
of Indian architectural style
along with elements of Islamic
architecture. The the style of Islamic
architecture. So that's the so-called
Indo-Saracenic style. But the question
really is that when you see a building
like this with a dome
and what looks like, you know, something
that resembles minarets, etc.,
is this really a fusion of Indian style
and and Islamic or Arabic style?
To understand
Before we understand that, let's see
what what uh
Islamic architecture looks like
according to Google.
Islamic architecture, all right?
So when we ask about Islamic
architecture, this is the kind of
imagery we get. This is the Taj Mahal.
This is whatever it is, I don't know
what it is. This is definitely somewhere
in the Middle East, possibly Abu Dhabi.
The Grand Mosque, perhaps.
Um
This is definitely more Persian.
This obviously has Persian or um
Central Asian elements
and so on. So these domes Domes in these
styles are considered to be Islamic
architecture today.
But is it really Islamic architecture?
What about architecture?
Arabic architecture. So once again it
will show you these domes.
See, once again it will even show you
the Taj Mahal as an example of
apparently Arabic architecture. But is
that correct?
So for that, let's let's do a different
kind of search.
Ancient Saudi
architecture. Now see what happens.
Look at this.
This is the original Arabic or Islamic
architecture.
Rectangles,
squares, squat shapes.
You don't see domes here.
Do you see domes?
You will not see domes anywhere in this.
So this is the true Islamic or Arabic
architecture style. Even in modern
buildings,
okay, you will see the same kind of
shapes. Squat shapes, rectangles, maybe
cylinders and so on. You don't see any
of the domes that
you know, Google will tell Google will
show you when it's giving you
examples of Islam so-called Islamic
architecture. What about ancient Omani
architecture?
Well, once again you see the same squat
shapes, mostly.
The same squat shapes again, rectangles,
etc.
What about ancient uh
Qatari
Qatari architecture. Once again,
it's going to show you the same old
squat shapes. So this is the actual
original
Arabic or Islamic architecture. Go back
to Saudi.
This is the true original intrinsic
Islamic and Arabic architecture. This is
what it looks like.
Okay? And when they show you
domes
like what we have with the Taj Mahal,
this is not Arabic architecture. This is
not true Islamic architecture.
This is the elements what we are seeing
here is the elements that the Arabs and
and
Islamic architects or whoever
incorporated
from non-Arabic non-Islamic cultures
such as India. These domes are
are signature of our signatures of
Indian architectural styles. And then
this was brought back into Arabia.
And today if you see modern Islamic
architecture,
it will look very much like you know the
domes of the Taj Mahal etc. So these
styles
were imported
from India.
>> [snorts]
>> Okay?
This is not or genuine intrinsic Islamic
or Arabic architecture. This is Indian
architecture which has influenced the
Islamic world
essentially through throughout the
Islamic world.
If you see something like this, well
this is this is the Hagia Sophia if I'm
not mistaken.
The Hagia Sophia
mosque
in Constantinople. Well this was the
Hagia Sophia church.
And this was
European Byzantine architecture.
But forget about that. We'll we'll look
at this. So what we see here is actually
a mosque in the Middle East which has
elements of Indian architectural styles.
Which is inspired by Indian
architectural styles.
So the Taj Mahal is Indian architecture.
It is not Arab architecture or Islamic
architecture. Let's be very clear about
this. All right? The domes came from
India. You also have domes
in in Gandhara in Afghanistan. What
about Central Asian Central Asian, okay?
Central Asian Islam What am I writing
here? Central Asian Islam Islamic
architecture. Well you see
these mosques like the Bibi Khanum
mosques mosque etc.
Okay? What about uh
Timur's Mausoleum?
Mausoleum.
So you will see Yeah, this. Once again
it has the dome etc. All of these styles
came out of India. These monuments that
were built in Central Asia were mostly
built by slaves who were enslaved in
India and taken to Central Asia. And
they chose the right kind of slaves.
They chose women and children for
I suppose you understand what reasons.
But they also chose highly skilled
craftsmen, architects,
workmen etc. who who would be able to
build construct buildings, design and
construct buildings such as these.
Um
And the The interesting thing is that a
lot of these buildings in Central Asia
okay, which are Islamic monuments, you
will see swastikas
swastikas embedded in the designs of
these buildings.
Which is also very interesting which
again points to Indians having
built these monuments. Okay. So I hope
that
throws light
on this matter.
Next question is by Rushabh Tari. Who
were the Romani people? So I have spoken
about the Romani people in the past, but
it's been a while.
It's been quite a while that I've spoken
about the Romani people and I'm sure
there are lots of new viewers on the
channel
who are not aware of what I've said in
the past about the Romani people. So
let's take this question all over again
a priori.
Who were the Romani people? What was
their relation to ancient and medieval
India? Were they part of the slave trade
of Turkic invaders of Central Asia? How
did they reach reach Europe? Was it
through crusades? The trade of Slavs as
slaves originating word slavery or any I
mean you're trying to put everything in
there. What role did they play in in
Europe? How and why were they persecuted
by Adolf Hitler's Holocaust policies?
Um
Tell their persecution and survival
story like that of the Jews. No, it's
very different from the Jews. Very very
very different. And can you mention a
few prominent Romani people? Okay.
The Romani people.
Let's begin with some prominent Romani
people, shall we?
Let's ask Google.
You know, famous Romani people.
Fa- famous
Romani people.
So
let's take a look at this. Charlie
Chaplin, Romani.
Ian Hancock. Yul Brynner, very famous
actor.
Uh Michael Caine, Rita Hayworth, very
famous uh
Hollywood actress. Alba Flores.
Alba Flores, in case you don't know she
uh Spanish actress who plays the role of
Nairobi or something in Money Heist or
something.
Jesús Castro.
Uh Michael Caine.
There's there's way more list of Romani
people. List of Romani people. Okay,
let's see here.
What about artists? Sandra Reath,
boxers, footballers. Oh, so many.
Ricardo Quaresma.
Uh Freddie Eastwood, of course. Uh Eric
Cantona, very mercurial very famous
French footballer. One of the all-time
greats. One of the all-time great
footballers for Manchester United. Eric
Cantona.
Uh
Where is Hristo Stoichkov? H H H H H H
H.
E F G H. Okay, Hristo Stoichkov is
missing from here.
What about
Rita Hayworth, very famous Hollywood
actress. Yul Brynner, once again very
famous great
uh Hollywood actor. Bob Hoskins, one of
the greats. Charlie Chaplin, I mean I
don't have to introduce who that is to
you, right? Musicians. Robert Plant of
Led Zeppelin. My God.
I mean in his youth he used to look like
a Viking with his blonde hair and blue
eyes, but he's of Romani Romani origin.
Bebe Rexha, Azis.
Um
I mean just the list just goes on and
on.
So I mean
so many. Talat Pasha, who we who we will
discuss later today. Talat Pasha.
One of the three
one of the members of the Turkish
triumvirate. The Young Turks
triumvirate. The three Pashas.
Um and so much more. Okay. So these are
some of the famous Romani people. I'm
sure I've missed a lot of these name lot
of the name. Andrea Pirlo, one of the
great Italian footballers. Yes, Andrea
Pirlo. Hristo Stoichkov. Uh
Croatian footballer who took
who took his country to the semi-finals
of the 1996 Football World Cup. He
scored a free kick against Germany, a
left footed curling free kick that went
into the right corner.
Because that's what life and so much
more. So now
that's
a small
number of examples of famous Romani
people. Now who are these Romani people?
Romani people
are of Indian origin.
They are a
very badly persecuted class of people in
Europe.
Now let's talk about their history.
What are Indian origin people doing in
Europe?
And now they're all across the world,
okay? But
they were in the past 1,000 years living
in Europe. How did they end up in
Europe? Indian origin people.
So there are various theories. We know
for sure that they are of Indian origin.
Their
genetics are unmistakably unambiguously
what they call Indo-Aryan.
Okay? Whatever that means.
Um
Genetically they they they they
they are very closely related to the
people of Western and Northern in North
North and in Northern Western India.
Gujarat, Sindh,
um
Rajasthan, Haryana, Punjab, these
regions. Okay? The Romani people are
most closely related to the people of
these modern Indian states.
Um The Romani language is classified as
a as a
pure Indo-Aryan language.
And if you look at Romani people, many
of them look very very Indian. Uh Alba
Flores for example, okay? Let's let's
see Alba Flores.
Alba Flores, Spanish actress. I mean
she's Spanish, but I mean take a look at
her.
If she's walking around in the in a
street in India, nobody's going to think
she's she's a foreigner, right?
Alba Flores and
yeah, so many other examples. So
they look very clearly Indian. They
speak an Indian
Western Indian origin language. Their
genetics are unambiguously Indian.
So how did they end up in Europe? And
there are multiple theories. So uh the
first Romani person to get a PhD to earn
a PhD is Dr. Ian Hancock who wrote the
book We are the Romani people
which I have recommended multiple times.
And according to him, according to Dr.
Ian Hancock,
the Romani people are of Rajputic
origin. That's what he says. So
what's it mean? It means that they were
the descendants of warriors. The the
Rajputs of Western India.
And maybe they were enslaved by the
Turks.
And
maybe the Turks took too many slaves and
then they released some of them and
forced them to go westwards into Europe
rather than go back in eastwards into
India. That's one theory.
Another theory is obviously rather be
similar that
whether or not they were of Rajput
origin, they were of
Western and Northern Indian origin. And
we know that the Turks took millions of
Indians as slaves.
Uh you know
uh the Ghurids and the Ghaznavids and so
on.
And they would take the slaves Indian
slaves mainly
you know, women and children, but also
males who were skilled
artisans
and craftsmen and architects and
musicians and whatnot. And they would
take them across what is now called the
Hindu Kush mountains, which killed
lots of Hindus. That's why it's called
the Hindu Kush mountains. And they would
be sold in the slave markets of
Samarkand, Bukhara, etc. in in Central
Asia.
And it's possible that maybe the Turks
took way too many slaves than they could
accommodate.
And then instead of massacring them on
Turkic soil, they may maybe decided
that, "You know what? We will release
them, but we will not allow them to go
back to India. We will force them to go
westwards."
And that's how
these people eventually ended up in
Europe.
And the past thousand or so years
they've been Europe in Europe. And the
initially the the people of Europe
regarded them as descendants of
Egyptians.
Egyptians became Egyptians became
Gypsies.
Right? So, that's why they are called
the Gypsies because the Europeans
initially believed that they were of
Egyptian origin.
And in Europe they have faced terrible,
horrific persecution for the past 1,000
years.
Much worse persecution than the Jews
have faced.
The Romanis have been enslaved. The
Romanis have been massacred. The Romanis
have been genocided. The Romanis, even
in the best of situations and
circumstances, have been treated like
outcasts and second-class not even
second-class citizens, non-citizens.
Not allowed to assimilate and not
allowed to live within society as a
distinct ethnic group.
Forced to live on the margins and
fringes of society.
Many of them were forcibly assimilated
into European society
by being made to
you know, lose their ethnic and cultural
identity.
The Romanis, wherever they went, they
had to
adopt the local religion. So, if you
look at Turkey for example today, okay,
which is at the crossroads between
what's
apparently the line between Europe and
Asia.
If you see Turkey,
at least 5% of Turkey's population is of
Romani origin.
And they're all Muslims. All of them.
Many of them, you know, are are various
kinds of skilled crafts people. Many of
them are are high-quality musicians and
so much more.
Um then you have lots about maybe 10%
possibly of Romania's population is of
Romani or Gypsy origin.
And they are very badly persecuted
there. So, what happens is that, you
know what? You take a bunch of people,
you force them to to live on the fringes
of society. You don't allow them
to to play a proper role in society.
So, you force them on the margins. You
don't allow them to have a proper
occupation, gainful occupation. You
don't allow them to
to be a regular part of society.
You make sure that they have no source
of income. You make sure that they have
no citizenship.
So, what will these people do? How will
they ensure that there is food on the
table?
Eventually they will have to turn to
criminal behavior. So, then you will
stereotype them as criminals.
And that's what's done in Europe. The
Romani people are stereotyped as as
criminals and petty thieves and whatnot.
And uh
you know, there's this tremendous stigma
stigma and bias against them. Where
whichever country the Romani people live
in, the police are special, you know,
especially harsh on them.
Uh in many countries they don't even
have citizenship documents.
They live in
uh wandering caravans and so on. And in
some countries they have been able to
assimilate better while maintaining a a
distinct identity. See, there's two
kinds of assimilation.
One one kind of assimilation is that
where a group of people is made to
forcibly lose their identity and
assimilate. So, you are the Romani
people. You have to give up your
language. You stop speaking your
language. You stop practicing your
religion. You stop calling yourself
Romani. You marry among the locals and
become white.
That is the erasure of identity. That's
been attempted on the Romanis. And
another kind
of assimilation is where you are allowed
to
to become an integral part of society,
to play an integral role in society like
all other people, but you're allowed to
maintain a distinct identity. For
example, if you look at France today,
you have Algerian origin French people
who maintain a distinct identity. We are
Algerians. We are Muslims.
But we are also French. If you look at
the United Kingdom,
you have Bangladeshi Pakistani origin
Muslims
who retain their Bangladeshi and
Pakistani identity. We are Bangladeshi
origin people. We are Pakistani origin.
We are Muslims and then we are British.
So, see you see, they are they are
playing
a central role in society.
They are not on the fringes on the
margins of society.
But they maintain their distinct
identity. That has never been allowed
for the Romani people. Never.
Uh in some some countries they've been
able to, you know, they've had better
luck. For example, like I said, Turkey.
In Turkey they have
been allowed to,
you know, quietly keep their Romani
identity as long as they
convert to Islam.
And as long as they don't
shout from the rooftops that we are
different.
So, in in Turkey,
the Romani are actually treated kind of
better than the Romani are treated in
in Europe as long as they
uh convert to Islam, which they have all
all converted. And as long as they don't
claim to be a separate entity. As long
as they say that we are Turks, there's
no problem.
In Spain, the Romani are are kind of
better off compared to other countries.
Um
you may have heard of the Spanish
national music,
flamenco music, Spain's national dance,
the flamenco dance. It's not Spanish.
It's Romani.
Okay? Spaniards did not invent flamenco
music or flamenco dance. The Romani
people invented it.
One of the most prominent forms of uh
you know,
jazz in the world is Gypsy jazz.
Um
one of the greatest of the Gypsy jazz
guitarists was uh
Django Django Reinhardt. What does
Django mean? The Let me show you.
Django Reinhardt, one of the greatest
guitarists of all time.
Django Reinhardt, okay?
He
played with only two fingers because he
had
he had lost the use of two fingers, the
last two fingers of his hand, in a fire
accident.
And despite playing with only two
fingers, he was one of he was one of the
greatest guitarists of all time. As you
can see, he looks very Indian. His name
was Django.
It actually means Jago.
What does Jago mean? It means wake up.
I think we all understand that, right?
Jago.
So, that became Django. It became
Europeanized.
Um
Yeah.
And so, the Romanis have been great
musicians. Robert Plant is one of the
greatest vocalists in rock music of all
time.
Um Django Reinhardt, one of the greatest
guitarists of all time. Biréli Lagrène,
another great guitarist who is a
contemporary of ours.
Uh so many great musicians, so many
great actors, Rita Hayworth, Charlie
Chaplin, Yul Brynner, so many great
singers, Elvis Presley.
Presidents of the United States.
There is a Romani origin president of
the United States.
His name
is William Blythe.
Have you heard of William Blythe? Let me
show you.
William Blythe.
Um
Okay, William Blythe III.
>> [laughter]
>> Bill Clinton.
What was his name at birth? He was born
what? Let's see.
He was born William Jefferson Blythe
III.
Okay?
His father is William Jefferson Blythe
Jr.
Um what's his uh background?
English and Scottish. Ha ha ha
The Blythe family is
prominent Gypsy family in England.
See,
you will find a lot of erasure of Gypsy
identity.
Because many people did it voluntarily
because they were afraid of being outed
as being Gypsy because then it would
bring a lot of stigma against them. So,
they would try to hide their Gypsy
identity.
That's why lots of famous people
have been confirmed that they are Gypsy
even though it's known that they are
Gypsy, you know,
uh that sort of thing.
Uh so, that's kind of the story of the
of the Romani people.
Indian origin people. A lot of them have
assimilated through blood, through
intermarriage, etc. and they've become
almost white. Um former president of
Brazil also was of Romani origin and
there's
Romani origin people all across the
world today.
Many of them may not be aware of their
ancestry. Many of them would be aware of
it. They would try to hide it. And some
of them are proud of it, especially in
Spain and in some parts of Europe where,
you know, being Gypsy, being of Romani
origin, as as long as you are famous and
rich person, is kind of regarded as
cool, perhaps.
Perhaps to some extent, especially if
you are very rich, like some flamenco
dancers and so on.
So, that's kind of this thing. And now
about the what happened to the Romanis
compared to what happened to Jews. The
German the Nazis tried to exterminate
the Romanis.
The Nazis tried to exterminate the
Romanis just like the same way they
tried to exterminate the Jews.
Okay, so but the Jewish persecution is
is celebrated or remembered across the
world as the Holocaust.
But what happened to the Romani people
is suppressed.
There is this guy called Elie Wiesel or
whatever, okay?
Let's see his name. Elie Wiesel.
Wiesel. This fellow. Okay, Romanian born
American etc. blah blah blah. Um,
Holocaust survivor. Now,
what about the Rom- you know, let's see.
Romani Romani Romani
publicized
Okay, so this is now being suppressed.
What he did, this fellow, Elie Wiesel,
is being suppressed.
See, Wikipedia no longer has references
to that.
Romani
denial
Okay, let's see.
Not Romania, Romani denial.
Elie Wiesel did not deny the Romani
>> [laughter]
>> Uh, very funny. I don't trust any of
these stupid AI systems.
Um,
he tried his best.
See, there was this Holocaust memorial
that
was
you know,
a Holocaust mem- memorial was supposed
to be built in the United States or
something and many people wanted the
the massacres and the genocide of the
Romani people also to be included in
that and this guy was against that.
So, he was like, you know, the Holocaust
is only for the Jews. What happened what
the Nazis did was only for the Jews and
we must not remember what happened to
the Romanis.
We don't exactly know how many Romani
were killed
by the Germans but the by the Nazis.
Possibly over a million.
And what is this called? So, the Nazis
have So, the Jews have something called
the Holocaust
of the Romani.
What is that called? Romani Holocaust.
It's called the Porajmos, right?
Porajmos.
Not sure what it means.
It's called the Porajmos.
Porajmos.
That's the Romani Holocaust. It was also
called the Kali Tras or something.
Kali Tras.
Yeah, Romani Holocaust.
I think all Indians can understand what
this word what this term means.
So, the Nazis tried to exterminate the
Romani.
Even though the Romani were actually
more Aryan
than the Nazis.
Uh, so yeah, that's the story of the
Romani people. And today they are still
persecuted horribly in many parts of
Europe.
In very civilized parts of Europe.
They are not even second class citizens.
They are non-citizens in many places.
They don't even have They are not even
allowed to have citizenship documents.
And that is what democratic Europe that
lectures the world about human rights
does to the Romani people who have been
living there for a thousand years.
Anyhow, that is the story of the Romani
people.
Sahasrarai
Okay, the question is
Sahasrarai says,
"Which are the descendants of the
Scythians nowadays? Did the Shakya clan
from whom Gautama Buddha came, does it
have a connection with the Scythians?
Who are the descendants of the Scythians
nowadays?"
I would say all people in northern and
western India
or the northern and western subcontinent
which starts from Gandhara, Afghanistan
all the way to Sindh, Balochistan
includes Punjab, Haryana, Kashmir,
Rajasthan, Gujarat
Sindh
Khyber Pakhtunkhwa etc. All of this
region
I would say the overwhelming majority of
people in this region will have some
Scythian ancestry.
No question about it.
Because the Scythians ruled these
regions.
They were the great Mahakshatrapas.
The western satraps. The great rule You
know,
they were great defenders of India.
They have gave us some of the greatest
kings we had.
They were mainly Shaivites.
The Mahakshatrapas who ruled in western
India were the lords and guardians and
protectors and servants of the great
Jyotirlinga of Somnath and so on. So,
most people
in the northern and western subcontinent
will have some Scythian ancestry.
You will not find anybody who's pure
Scythian. There's no such thing as a
pure ethnicity, pure but the Scythians
were themselves of Indian ancestry.
When the Scythians came to India,
assimilated into into Indian society,
there is not one record anywhere of any
clashes between Indians and Scythians
because we were the same people
essentially.
Um, so yeah, that that's about the
descendants of the Scythians. Now, the
Shakya clan.
See, Gautama Buddha
is called the Shakyamuni.
Right?
Shakyamuni.
Uh, you will see lots of literature
you know, calling him the ski- the
Shakyamuni instead of Gautama Buddha.
So, that's one of the epithets epithets
of Gautama Buddha, Shakyamuni. And
that's because he was
descended from these Shakya clan of
northern India.
The Shakya clan
you could say Shakya was the Shakya
people were a clan in
um
it was kind of a Janapada, not a
Mahajanapada but a Janapada, you know, a
self- governing uh,
small republic kind of thing
in northern India parts of which are now
Nepal currently.
In in more recent times in the past
couple of hundred years.
Uh,
but now the question is the Shakya
people
to whose lineage Gautama Buddha belonged
were they related to the Scythians?
That's the big question.
So, Gautama Buddha, let's understand the
chronology.
Chronology.
How does it work?
See, chronologically we have Gautama
Buddha who lives maybe in the 6th
century BC, maybe 5th century BC.
Let us say roughly approximately
500 BC.
Okay, roughly, give or take. We don't
know exactly what the specific years
were but let's say roughly 500 BC is
Gautama Buddha's time.
When did the Shakas
the Scythians re-enter India after a
long
period of like 2, 3,000 years of
wandering in Central Asia.
When did the Scythians re-enter India?
The Scythians
re-entered India maybe about
200 BC
or 150 BC.
Right?
And the Scythians started entering India
because of pressure from the Kushans.
And the Kushans were pressurized
pressurizing the Scythians by coming
westwards because of pressure from the
Huns.
If you look at the map, it will make it
will make more sense.
Where is map? Yes, let's find map.
Um, all right, here's the map. So, let's
understand the chronology. Around 500 BC
in northern India we have Gautama Buddha
who's living. Now, in the region which
is now Mongolia, in this region you had
a group of people called the Xiongnu
Xiongnu.
The Huns.
They were the ancestors of of of the
Mongols of today
and also the Turkic peoples who live in
various parts of the world.
So, the Turks and the Mongols have the
same ancestors, the Huns who lived
initially, originally in the region that
is now Mongolia.
Now, the Huns suddenly around 500, 400
BC they become a big powerful force
and they spread out westwards.
Now, in the Tarim River region, in this
region, in what is now so-called
Xinjiang occupied by China, you had the
Kushans who lived here. At this time
this region was more fertile, you had
more uh,
the the Tarim River was very, you know,
it it it was a major river in the
Kushans they lived in this region. So,
the the Huns start coming westwards so
the Kushans are forced to flee westwards
because the Huns were more powerful.
And they start going into into parts of
the of Central Asia where you had the
Scythians who were living for like 2,000
years.
So, the Scythians were less powerful
than the Kushans so they start going
southwards into the subcontinent
where you had in the northern and
western part of the of the subcontinent
at the time you had Indo-Greek kingdoms.
So, the Scythians start pressurizing the
Indo-Greek kingdoms and slowly replace
them, defeat the Indo-Greeks and become
the rulers themselves slowly slowly.
So, the Scythians enter India, the
Shakas enter India maybe 200 BC, maybe
150 BC. Around that time.
But that is much later than 500 BC when
Gautama Buddha
lived in northern India.
So, the Scythians come later.
And the Shakyas are come much before.
The I'm not saying the Scythians
suddenly appeared out of nowhere 150 or
200 BC. The Scythians were living in
Central Asia far away from north India.
But in north India at the time 500 BC we
had a clan called the Shakya people, the
Shakya clan clan. So, most likely there
is no connection between the Shakya
people of northern India
and the Scythians who were then at that
time in Central Asia.
Most likely no connection. Some
historians will tell you that maybe the
Shakya people are connected to the
Scythians, maybe they are a branch of
the Scythians, they were a branch of the
Scythians, maybe they were descendants
of of the Scythians, but that's highly
unlikely in my opinion based on the
chronology that we have just discussed.
So, the Shakya clan most likely did not
have a connection with the Scythians.
Kante says, "Can you make a video on the
Alans tribe, please?"
I will
Let's discuss the Alans tribe.
It's not a tribe.
It's not a tribe. It's a It's an
ethnicity, let's say.
So,
Alzat,
what is Alzat?
The Alzat people
were Jats.
Now, I have made I have
video clips on this channel in which I
explain the origins, the possible
origins of the Jat people. So, I'll not
go into all that all over again. But,
the Jat people
are people who even today live in large
parts of the subcontinent, northern and
western subcontinent.
Right? Including India and Pakistan.
Some of them are Muslim, some of them
are Hindu, some of them are Sikh.
Right? We have very famous Jat people.
Including Maharaja Ranjit Singh.
Right?
The founder of the Sikh Empire. And and
many more famous Jat people.
So, the Alzat
people who lived in West Asia
were descendants of the Jat They were
Jats themselves.
So,
you see, according to Islamic sources,
Arabic Islamic sources, the Alzat
people, they came from the Indus, the
Sindhu
Valley region, the Sapta Sindhu region,
but southern part of that, which is
Sindh-Balochistan.
And
they went westwards. They were settled
by the Sasanian Empire in various parts
of
you know, southern parts of Persia.
And after the
attempted invasions of Sindh by the
Arabs, more Jat people went westwards
into West Asia.
And even before the attempted invasion
of Sindh by the by
Bin Qasim etc., you had Alzat people
living in West Asia.
And it is said
by
by Islamic
chroniclers and historians that the
prophet of Islam, Prophet Muhammad
himself had dealings
with Alzat people. Now, what kind of
dealings you can look it up themselves
You can look it up yourself. I'll not go
into that.
Uh but, various kinds of dealings with
Alzat people.
So, it's Indian origin Jat people
who were living initially in the
southern part
of the Sindhu River Basin,
the Sindh and Balochistan regions, who
then
went traveled westwards and settled in
southern parts of Iran, then they
settled in Iraq. They were present in
Arabia during the time of the prophet of
Islam.
And eventually
they simply assimilated into Arabic
society and into Islamic society. They
obviously converted to Islam. They
fought in many battles and there was a
Alzat rebellion also.
Uh
against one of the caliphates. Was it
the Abbasid or Rashidun caliphate? One
of those one of those two caliphates.
And eventually, after the the quashing
of the Alzat rebellion, many of the
Alzat people were
forcibly relocated
from West Asia
all the way
to to to
what's now what was then the Byzantine
Empire.
So, they were
they went further westwards.
They were taken further westwards and
they were settled in in
what is now parts of Turkey.
Right?
So, Indian origin people all across the
place, all the way from Sindh and
Balochistan into southern
Persia,
further west into various parts of Iraq,
then further west and south into the
Arabian Peninsula,
all the way westwards to uh
to the Judea region, and further west
into uh what is now Turkey.
All across this place, you had Alzat
people who
uh
were settled in these parts
of the world. Eventually, they simply
assimilated into the local populations
and
um
today, we don't know who are the
descendants of the Alzat. Or maybe we
do, some of them.
Some of them maybe uh you can tell. I
mean, if you look at see,
there's a reason why a lot of Arabic
people look Indian.
There's two reasons. One, they could be
descendants of the Alzat people, of the
Jats.
Two, the other obvious reason is because
the the Arabs took a lot of Indian women
as slaves. And the offspring of those
women obviously will have Indian
appearances. Right?
So, you will see a lot of Arabic people
looking Indian.
Some of them look like uncles from
Haryana.
A great example is Saddam Hussein.
>> [clears throat]
>> Have you seen what he looked what he
looked like? Saddam Hussein, the late uh
dictator of Iraq.
I mean, he looked like a typical in
you know,
elderly gentleman, middle-aged gentleman
from let's say Haryana. Saddam
Hussein. What did he look like? Oh my
god, they've chosen the worst possible
image.
This gentleman, he has a
distinctive Indian appearance, doesn't
he?
Um
Saddam Hussein al-Tikriti.
Oh yeah, there there he is with a cigar.
Nice. So, uh
Saddam Hussein, he looked definitely
Indian. His sons, one of his sons'
names, what was his name? Uday Uday
Hussein, right? That's a Sanskrit name.
Um so, it is said that Saddam Hussein
was of Alzat
heritage. Okay, Saddam Hussein
Indian
ancestry.
Um Qais al-Ghazali Saddam Hussein DNA
analysis proved his Indian origins. So,
this is
this is apocryphal evidence. It's not
definitive evidence. It is somebody
saying that some analysis happened and
it proved his Indian origins. The
Americans most likely did DNA tests
on Saddam Hussein's DNA samples, but we
don't know what the results were. But,
it looks like he was of Alzat ancestry.
So, that's kind of about the Alzat
people. They were Jats from India who
settled all across West Asia and the
Arabian Peninsula and even Turkey, the
the regions that were part of the
Byzantine Empire. And then over time,
they simply assimilated into the local
populations. And some people clearly
still you can see that they have Indian
ancestry in these parts of the world.
So, that's about the Alzat people. They
are not a tribe.
They are the Jats. The Jats are not a
tribal people, right? What's What's a
tribe? What's the difference between a
tribe and something else?
A tribe, the definition is that it's a
small, isolated group of people who live
in a way that's isolated from the rest
of humanity. That's a tribe.
Now,
the Alzat The Jats are not not a tribe.
They're not a tribal people. They are a
big, large, robust uh you could say
subset of the Indian population.
All right.
Shub says, "Can human-made tools
discovered in Tamil Nadu
that date back to 3 lakh years, 300,000
years before today,
can that challenge the out-of-Africa
migration theory? Does it mean possi-
possibly that humans may have originated
from India?" Okay.
So, we have stone tools that have been
found in
I forget the name of the place. One
place in Tamil Nadu, another place in
Karnataka. And these stone tools date
back not 3 lakh years, they date back
potentially
1 and 1/2 million years before today. 15
lakh years before today. 15 1.5 to 1
million years before today.
That's What is it? I don't
Okay, I forget the name, but yeah. So,
you have stone tools made by archaic
humans
that have been discovered in various
parts of India,
Tamil Nadu as well as Karnataka, that
date between a million to a million and
a half years before today.
That's way before the so-called
out-of-Africa migration. The
out-of-Africa migration is said to have
happened between
between 80 to 55
thousand years before today.
Less than 1 lakh years before today.
Right?
But, we have stone tools in India that
date back potentially
million and a half years before today.
Million and a half years before today.
So, does that completely destroy the
out-of-Africa migration theory?
Does it now?
And we also have
uh
fossil human remains from the Narmada
from the Narmada Valley that date back
to what, 3 lakh years before today?
Roughly 300,000 years before today.
Now, what is all this? Does it not
destroy debunk the out-of-Africa
migration theory?
The thing is this,
the remains that we find
in the Narmada the Narmada Valley,
those remains are not of Homo sapiens.
Those are remains of Homo erectus most
likely, an archaic human species.
And the stone tools that we find in uh
Tamil Nadu and Karnataka that date back
to a million and a half years before
today,
those once again were most likely made
by Homo erectus. They are very similar
to other stone tools you find in other
parts of Eurasia,
which are definitely made by Homo
erectus.
So, these are archaic humans who lived
in the Indian subcontinent
before Homo sapiens emerged
in the fossil record. So, the oldest
evidence of Homo sapiens is about
400,000 years before today in Jebel
Irhoud, North Africa. That's the oldest
fossil remains that we have of our
species.
Okay, modern humans, Homo sapiens. So,
these human-made tools discovered are
not made by Homo sapiens. They are made
by an older archaic species
of humans. Obviously, our relatives, but
not our ancestors.
Our relatives, not our ancestors, Homo
erectus.
And that is fine. That does not have any
consequence of the on the out of Africa
migration theory, which is a theory
with evidence, which has evidence,
obviously, that's why it's widely
accepted. And this theory is about the
dispersion of Homo sapiens out of
Africa.
It doesn't say anything about Homo
erectus or Homo anything else, Homo
neanderthalis, etc. It's only about how
Homo sapiens, us, us, how did we emerge
out of Africa and populate the world.
That's the out of Africa migration
theory, and I've spoken about it many
times, so I'll not go into the details.
Uh but that's the deal. Okay, so these
stone tools, they didn't do not
challenge the out of Africa migration
theory. They don't uh mean that humans
originated in India, nothing like that.
Look, if new evidence appears, I will
revise my understanding of how the world
is.
But based on the best evidence that we
have today, the out of Africa migration
theory is the best theory that we have
so far. In the future, if more new
evidence emerges, maybe genetic
evidence, maybe archaeological evidence,
maybe fossil evidence, or whatever,
then based on that, I will be happy to
revise my understanding of the world.
But right now, this is the best theory.
Okay, Rohan B says, "We know that
ancient Indians during the Vedic period
relied on oral tradition to pass on
knowledge.
What could have been the potential
hurdles which prevented our ancestors
from storing information in the form of
writing?
And when did Indians actually take up
And I request last week's science
special was one of your best episodes in
recent times. Science has few takers,
unfortunately.
So, could you please have at least one
science specific episode a month? I will
be happy to do that.
I know that it will have very little
viewership because nobody cares about
science, but I I'll still do that. Um
I'll see, maybe once a month, maybe once
in a while, but I'll do that. Okay, so
now, about the question.
Um we know that
the Vedas were transmitted
orally. At least
one of the modes of transmission of the
Vedas was oral transmission.
In which
our ancestors relied on their memory
to transmit
the the entire corpus of the Vedas
exactly syllable by syllable without
making a single mistake.
And today also you have
you have people who have
who are continuing the tradition.
They have memorized the entire corpus of
the Vedas. Some people would
memorize the Rigveda. Some people would
memorize other Vedas. Some people would
memorize all Vedas if it's possible, but
it's possible. Human beings are capable
of incredible feats.
And they would not merely memorize the
words.
They'll be able to
to to recite
the shlokas
syllable by syllable without making a
single mistake, which means that when
they recite the shlokas,
they are reciting it exactly
the way
the Vedas were recited several thousand
years ago. Exactly the same
pronunciations, the same ucharas.
So, that's one mode of transmission of
the Vedas, oral transmission.
Now, we know about the Zoroastrians, and
they have these flames, right?
They have these fire temples, Agni
temples,
and they have these flames that are
burning in these temples. You go to
various Zoroastrian Parsi temples in
India.
I mean, we don't go into the temples
because those are only for the Parsis,
and we respect that. But they have these
fires
that have been burning for centuries,
and they tend the fire. They don't allow
it
to go out. They don't allow anything to
extinguish the fire. And they've been
tending these fires for centuries, and
some of the fires came from Iran, from
Persia,
when the Zoroastrians fled the Arabic
invasion.
Let's That's more than a thousand years
ago.
So, they have
kept the fire burning for over a
thousand years.
Our people, our ancestors kept the the
the fire burning, so to say,
metaphorically, for the transmission of
the Vedas for several thousand years.
Imagine that.
So, if you have someone who's who can
recite, let's say, the Rigveda in its
entirety,
that person was taught by somebody who
was taught by somebody else. And if you
take that chain backwards, you're going
to go back all the way to, I don't know,
6000 BC or something.
That's the kind of connection these
people have.
That's incredible. So, that's
>> [clears throat]
>> the oral mode of transmission of the
Vedas, okay?
Now,
what potential hurdles could have
prevented them
from storing information in the form of
writing?
Well, the only potential hurdle
that would have prevented them from
storing information in the form of
writing
would have been the
non-existence of writing. So, in there
would have been a time in our history,
ancient history, when writing was not
yet invented.
Right?
And that would be the only thing that
would prevent them from storing it.
Otherwise,
there would be people who would recite
the Vedas, but there would be people who
would write it down, too.
Because both Because storing their
knowledge in two forms is more
advantageous than for storing it in just
one form, or transmitting it in in just
form one form.
So, then that
takes us to the question of when
did Indians start
using
a script
for writing, which means the question
actually is
which is the oldest script that we know
of in the Indian subcontinent, and how
old is it?
So, we know there are scripts like
Brahmi, Kharosthi, and all kinds of
Brahmi or derived scripts, like
Devanagari, like the Sharada lipi, like
the various Southeast Asian scripts. All
these scripts are derived from the
Brahmi script.
There's a Kharosthi script, also. Uh
forget about the Kharosthi right now.
So, we have the Brahmi script that
may date back to maybe 1000 BC,
possibly.
Possibly.
But before the Brahmi script, which
script did we have?
It was the Saraswati Sindhu script,
the so-called Harappan script or Indus
Valley script.
And if you look at Wikipedia today, it
will say it's undeciphered.
Well, it's been deciphered
by Bharat Rao, also known as Iravatham,
and it turns out to be Sanskrit.
Vedic Sanskrit, late Vedic Sanskrit.
Sanskrit. It is Sanskrit.
So,
and you will see that there is a clear
transition between the so-called
Harappan
symbols or characters to the Brahmi
characters. So, which indicates that
Brahmi has evolved out of the old
so-called Harappan script or Saraswati
script.
And the oldest examples that we have of
the Saraswati script
date back to about
about
3000 BC or something,
which is 5000 years before today,
roughly.
If you ask Wikipedia, it will give you
something similar.
Roughly. Okay, let's see. In it will say
Indus script, right? Harappan script or
something. Indus script.
So, undeciphered, blah blah blah,
nonsense. So, what's the oldest
It will say 2800 BC,
or maybe proto-script from 3500 BC,
which is like five and a half thousand
years before today.
So, listen.
When it comes to archaeology
in the Saraswati Sindhu region,
we have not even excavated excavated
1% of the archaeological sites
that that exist
in this region, in the Saraswati Sindhu
region,
the the Sapta Sindhu region.
We have
excavated less than 1% of the
archaeological sites. And based on that
tiny little
amount of excavations we've done,
we know that the oldest example is about
of the Saraswati Sindhu script is about
five and a half thousand years old.
So, imagine we explore excavate
everything, then I'm sure it will go
back
a thousand or two thousand years,
possibly.
But based on the information that we
have right now, it's 3500 BC, the oldest
evidence that we have, which is five and
a half thousand years before today.
So, when did Indians actually take up
writing? Based on the best evidence,
it's five and a half thousand years
before today.
So, I suppose that's when we started
possibly started
writing the Vedas down
in
the form of a written script, possibly.
Of course, when it comes to the actual
ancient documents that [clears throat]
we have, the Vedas, those are most
likely written on birch bark, most
likely most likely written in
the Sharada script or something. I'm not
sure which script it was.
And that dates back to the past 2000
years only.
Uh because see birch bark etc. All these
perishable
media on which you can write, those
media are perishable and they
disintegrate easily especially in a hot
humid climate that the kind of climate
you have in the many parts of India.
And obviously the Vedas are so vast that
you can't write them on rock.
And we did not have the practice of
writing on clay tablets like the
Mesopotamians etc. had.
Uh but
the oldest evidence of writing in India
from the Indian subcontinent is from
about 3,500 BC roughly.
Which would indicate that that's when
Indians most likely took up writing.
Most probably before that somewhat, but
that's the best evidence that we have.
And I think that that's would that would
be the time around which maybe our
ancestors started writing it down.
So yeah, that's the best I can
That's the best we can
um
guess
or calculate based on the best
information that we have.
Matt and cflmao
says, "Why didn't Russia engage in naval
colonialism
and imperialism?" That's an interesting
question, great question.
We have powers.
We have states
like
Spain
Portugal
England
the Dutch
the the Danes etc.
who tried
to engage in naval colonialism
and imperialism. The Spaniards
they conquered the Americas and did all
did all kinds of fantastic wonderful
wonderfully barbaric things there.
They wiped out entire populations. They
genocided entire populations. The
Portuguese
went eastwards
and they discovered discovered India.
And then they tried similar barbaric
things in India.
Then you had
the the Dutch who also came to India who
also went to who also went to the
the Indonesian islands
and tried similar things there
with less success.
Then you had the Danes who also had an
East India company, the Danish East
India company. And then you had the
English who did untold brutality and
barbarism
not just in India but also in the
Americas.
And all of these these empires of these
these colonial powers were naval in
nature.
But then you have Russia.
And Russia doesn't do any of that.
And the question is, "Why?"
Why didn't Russia start an East India
company and send ships
to India?"
Why didn't they do that?
Well, there's multiple answers for that.
And
the biggest clues lie in geography.
Let's take a look at the map
so that we understand what we are
dealing with here. We're dealing with
Russia.
Now
So here's a map of Eurasia.
Now the original Russia okay, from 500
years ago
was simply
um what what
is now Ukraine and the Moscow region.
Okay, more or less. Ukraine was called
Ukraina at the time, which means the
borderlands. The borderlands of what?
The borderlands of Russia.
The original capital of the Rus people
was Kiev.
k i e v Kiev
And then later after the end of the
Mongol yoke
the capital became became Moscow,
Muscovy. And then from there the the
Russian empire started expanding. Okay,
now if you look at the geography. So
originally 500 years ago roughly
Russia was this small region and all of
this Russia today
was non-Russian.
They had no Russian Russian presence
there. And then in the 16th, 17th, 18th,
19th centuries the Russians started
expanding eastwards further and further
eastwards. They came into conflict with
the Tatars.
Uh significant conflicts with the Tatars
in Omsk. Where is Tomsk? Tomsk over
here.
Krasnoyarsk, the red city and so much
more. And they kept on going eastwards
and
So that was their modus operandi. If you
look at Russia
okay, even if you look at modern Russia
today which stretches from Eastern
Europe all the way to the Far East of
Asia you will see that they have
ports
like Murmansk which is in the Barents
Sea.
Um
the USSR had ports like Esto you know
Riga, Tallinn etc.
And eventually you had Konigsberg or
Kaliningrad. But all of these ports in
the Baltic Sea once again
the ports that Russia had, they are
frozen for a significant portion of the
year. The ports in the Arctic Circle,
they're also frozen most of the year.
And the ports that they have in the Far
East of Russia even Vladivostok
even these ports are frozen
you know, for significant
portions of every year. So when you have
no access to warm water ports
when you don't have access to the open
oceans, maybe the either the Atlantic or
the Pacific oceans
then how do you become
a naval a major naval power? You can't.
It's impossible.
Icebreaker technology even today you
can't use it to you know
you can use icebreakers only for very
specific tasks.
For very specific purposes.
You can't
have a new I mean you have nuclear
icebreakers and all. But icebreakers are
a very specialized kind of ships
a kind of ship and they can't be used
for
multiple purposes.
So and
before the 20th century icebreakers they
don't even exist.
That's why Russia never became a major
naval power. They decided to become
a continental power, a Eurasian power.
And they kept expanding eastwards
eastwards eastwards. They kept gobbling
up territories um that
that that belong to the various Turkic
peoples like the Tatars
like the Tungusic peoples, like the
Mongolians north of Mongolia is another
part of Mongolia which is now part of
Russia.
And all the way further east further
east further east all the way until
you know
up to the Far East of Russia which abuts
on the um
on the uh
Western Pacific
coast.
So that was the deal with Russia. And
Russia What what was the financial
impetus
or incentive for colonizing
for being a continental colonizing
power? It was the fur trade.
Okay?
The fur trade
fueled all of this colonizing. And
eventually the Russians did occupy did
establish
a colony on a different continent which
was Alaska.
All right?
But then by the
by the roughly middle of the 18th
century, 19th century, middle of the
19th century
when the fur trade started started
winding down
and when the Russians started facing
pressure from the Americans and the
British in Alaska
they decided that instead of fighting
for Alaska let's just sell it off to the
Americans. And that's what they did. So
they gave up the colony they had
established, very large colony of
Alaska.
And there were times when the Russians
had a reasonably powerful navy but that
navy was deployed in the Black Sea
in uh the Baltic Sea etc. for mainly
defensive purposes.
And also sometimes in the Mediterranean
Sea via the Bosphorus, the Strait of the
Dardanelles, Gallipoli etc.
So that was the thing.
Um
geography tells us
that it was not possible for Russia to
become a major naval power and that's
one of the reasons one of the factors
that contributed to the decline and
eventual dissolution of the USSR.
That the Anglo
Saxon empire controlled the oceans and
the trade routes.
They had unfettered access to all the
oceans.
The Pacific Ocean, the Atlantic Ocean,
the Mediterranean Sea
even the Indian Ocean
right?
And the Russians did not have access to
any
proper warm water port.
And
that explains a lot why Russia did not
engage in naval colonialism and
imperialism. Russia was an imperialistic
power.
I'm not sure if it still is. Some people
would like to say it is, but
historically it was. It was an
expansionist empire and it expanded in a
continental fashion, not
intercontinentally
through naval operations. Naval
operations are very expensive and you
need to be really good
at logistics and whatnot to succeed at
that, which is something only the
British were able to do eventually.
So Russia adopted a totally different
approach and it was very successful at
that.
Amisha says, "Why is Leonardo da Vinci
regarded as such an amazing inventor?
Did Leonardo da Vinci invent anything
that was actually built, adopted and
widely used?"
Leonardo da Leonardo da Vinci. So when
did he live? I can tell you about him,
but let's first look at
uh the time period when Leonardo da
Vinci lived. During the Renaissance,
wasn't it?
Leonardo
da Vinci
So yeah.
1452 to 1519
is the time period when Leonardo da
Vinci lived and he was
>> [clears throat]
>> Excuse me.
And yeah, he lived in Italy and he died
in France.
So that
that establishes when Leonardo da Vinci
lived. Now, see, he's regarded as a
great inventor, isn't he?
Um and why is he regarded as a great,
fantastic, amazing inventor?
Did he
invent anything that was actually built,
adopted, widely used? Not quite.
So why is he still rightfully regarded
as an amazing inventor?
Because of his vision.
Because
of the groundbreaking, pathbreaking
novel
original work he did. He was a
visionary. He could see the future of
technology. Okay? Um
his ideas
had extraordinary breadth,
had tremendous detail.
They were incredibly original. He had
thousands of ideas
in various domains, uh engineering,
mechanics, anatomy.
And
and he he recorded all these ideas in
his notebooks.
His inventions were not really
constructed or used broadly. And
during his lifetime,
his ideas had very
limited or modest impact. Okay? And his
inventions did not really enter
practical use. But
what he
what he did is he filled thousands of
notebook pages with incredible designs
for futuristic machines.
He
designed hydraulic systems. He designed
weapons.
He designed uh
archit- architectural projects.
He studied anatomy. I'm sure he did it
illicitly, illegally. I'm sure you can't
really uh
dissect human bodies. You could not you
were not allowed to dissect human
bodies, but he still did that. And he
and he filled so many notebooks with you
know
with diagrams of human anatomy.
And
the kind of
machines he imagined,
okay, or he anticipated, include
parachutes, include tanks, include
helicopters.
Not the modern-day kind of helicopter,
but the idea for a helicopter, right?
That sort of thing.
His notebooks are filled with technical
drawings, which are incredibly clear,
very advanced, very sophisticated. There
is something called exploded diagrams.
Do you know what an exploded diagram is
like what it is? Let me show you.
So he came up with what is now widely
used, that is the exploded diagram.
Let's take a look at it.
So this is an example These are examples
of exploded diagrams.
And Leonardo da Vinci pioneered this.
Nobody had come up with exploded
diagrams before him as far as we know.
He also had these cutaway views.
Cutaway views.
So these are called cutaway views, you
know?
As you can see, it's like you've sliced
into
into other house
or an aircraft. So that these things are
called cutaway views. And these are now
pretty standard
uh practices in engineering design.
But
da Vinci came up with this about 500
years ago and nobody else had done that
before. So he was an incredible artist.
He was very meticulous in his
observations, in his analysis. He had
incredible insights into the future. He
had incred- incredible mechanical
insights. So he combined these
qualities, artistic skill,
meticulous observation, mechanical
insight, and all of these things
together and all the ideas, the
thousands of ideas he he came up with in
thousands of notebook pages,
um
these are what, you know,
made him the symbol of the universal
genius or the
uh the archetype of the polymath, right?
And
that's the reason. So um
what are the famous machines he came up
with? Flying machines, um
weapons like crossbows,
helicopters, uh armored vehicles.
All of these concepts that he came up
with, they became reality only in the
20th century.
So he imagined those things roughly 500
years or 400 years before they became
reality. Not in the shape and form that
he imagined, but the concept was
absolutely correct, right?
>> [clears throat]
>> So these are the reasons why he's
regarded as an amazing inventor, as as a
genius, as a polymath. And obviously, he
was a great artist, fantastic art
artist, and he did a lot of uh
engineering work.
Um he he
you know, constructed canals. He
built
uh fortifications.
He
he
worked on multiple on on many
architectural and engineering projects,
right?
So that's the thing about Leonardo da
Vinci. He did not actually come with
things that were
that fructified during his life during
his lifetime. But his vision, his
foresight was incredible.
And he
imagined
things clearly, conceptually.
And those things eventually became
reality. And that's why
he is regarded as such a great inventor,
as as a polymath, as an absolute genius.
Sharma says, "I was researching Ottoman
era slavery of Europeans. Grok told me
Grok
Grok told me that the Crimean slave
trade and the Barbary slave trade
combined enslaved between 6 to 9 million
mostly white women for four centuries.
Doesn't this contradict the leftist
paradigm that white people were never
enslaved or oppressed. American slavery
gets brought up endlessly endless times
by leftists, yet they never talk about
the enslavement of millions of Europeans
by the colonial Islamic Ottoman Empire
out of sheer ignorance. Why isn't this
talked about in academia? I think it
deserves more attention. Okay.
I'm not sure if the leftists say that
the white people were never enslaved. I
personally am not aware of that. Maybe
I've missed something, maybe I've not, I
don't know.
But
the Crimean slave trade
and the Barbary slave trade are a real
thing. I'm not sure how many
people how many women were enslaved.
But this happened in two phases. And
before the Crimean slave trade and the
Barbary slave trade, you had the trans-
trans-African what the African slavery.
The Arabs
would procure, let's say, labor from
Africa.
Okay?
And millions of Africans were enslaved
as a consequence. And millions of
Indians were enslaved by the way.
By the way.
Now, when it comes to the
Crimean slave trade and the Barbary
slave trade,
there is one factor in common between
these two.
One factor in common. What is that
common factor between these two?
It is the Ottoman Empire.
Okay?
So the Crimean slave trade
centers around the Black Sea.
Let's take a look at the map. We're
talking about the Black Sea region,
Central Asia, Eastern Europe, etc.
Uh the Black Sea is south of Ukraine as
I'm sure we know by now.
This is the Black Sea. And the Crimean
slave trade
centers around the Black Sea. It
centered around the Black Sea, okay?
So what was the deal?
You had
Italians and Genoese slave traders
who were slaving after out of a place
called Theodosia.
It's now called Feodosia.
It was earlier called Theodosia and even
before that it was called Caffa.
So this was the center of the slave
trade, the Crimean
slave trade. And this obviously this
peninsula is the Crimean peninsula,
right? Sevastopol, Simferopol, etc.
This is Crimea.
So
out of Caffa,
which is now called Feodosia, you had
the slave trade that operated from
there. And it was Italian and Genoese
merchants. Where is Genoa?
Where is Genoa? Genoa is here.
Genoese merchants,
they
were doing the slave trade uh
where have we gone?
From the Black Sea region.
Uh and they were enslaving Europeans in
in in selling them to the Ottomans.
So essentially, it's sometime in the
15th century, late 15th century, that
the Ottoman Empire
conquered the Crimean region, the Black
Sea region, okay?
And you had something called the Crimean
Khanate.
You had the khans of Crimea. They were
distant offshoots of the erstwhile
Mongol Empire. The Mongols had
occupied Russia
for a couple of centuries. And then they
left behind khanates and there was a
Crimean Khanate,
which was an Islamic
governance system, an Islamic kingdom,
you could say.
And the Crimean Khanate was conquered by
the Ottoman Empire around the late 15th
century.
So the Crimean Khanate was allowed to
continue by the Ottomans as a vassal
state.
And it became a major supplier of slaves
to the Ottoman Empire.
Okay? And uh
by the 16th century, 17th century, the
uh Crimean Khanate would uh you know
send raids into all the way to Poland,
all the way to Lithuania.
They would send raids into
into into Russia,
into Where is Hungary? Where is Hungary?
Have we lost Hungary?
Uh here is Hungary. Hungary, the
Balkans,
the Baltic region,
all over the place.
So the Crimean Khanate Khanate was very
powerful. It was a very powerful vassal
of the Ottoman Empire. And they would
twice a year, roughly, launch slave
slaving raids all across the region, all
the way to Russia, all the way into uh
Poland, Lithuania, Hungary,
uh the Balkan region, all the way.
And uh
they would export these slaves, mainly
women, also children, mainly women, to
the Ottoman Empire. Okay?
>> [clears throat]
>> And then obviously like like
every empire, every every state, you
have a decline.
So the Russian Empire starts becoming
powerful in the 17th, 18th centuries,
okay?
And then there is a Russian Russian
Russo Russo Turkic Turkish war
uh
sometime in the 18th century.
And the Russians win
the war against the Turks, against the
Ottoman Empire. And the Russians, what
do they do? They annex Crimea.
Crimea was annexed by the Russians. And
that brought an end to the Crimean slave
trade. And that was the end of that
barbaric era where the Crimean Khanate
would take millions of European women as
slaves and sell them to the Ottomans.
So that's the Crimean slave trade. Now
let's talk about the Barbary slave
trade. That's
slave trade operating in the
Mediterranean region. Barbary The
Barbary Coast was the North African
Coast Coast.
You know, the coast of Morocco, Algeria,
Tunisia, Libya, essentially. That was
the Barbary Coast. And you had
slave trading pirates, essentially.
Okay? Who would operate from North
Africa.
North Africa was Islamic, it was Muslim.
And they would operate out of this
region. And they would launch raids on
Europe.
And they would procure slaves. Okay?
And they would sell it to the Ottoman
Empire.
>> [clears throat]
>> So where would they launch the slave
these raids? They would launch launch
raids,
pirate raids, slave capturing raids on
Spain,
on Italy. Obviously that makes sense. On
France also, France also makes sense.
But also eventually they started making
raids all the way to Britain, to
Ireland, and even Iceland. And they
would capture mainly
women.
And they would bring them back to places
like let's say Tripoli, Algiers, Tunis.
These were all slave markets. And from
there the the goods were transported
to the Ottoman Empire, Constantinople,
and other places. Right?
So uh
so the the the Barbary slave trade you
could say its roots were in the Roman
Roman period. But uh it became a big
deal in the 15th, 16th, 17th centuries,
okay?
Uh I think the 17th century was the peak
of the Barbary slave trade. And
eventually the European powers became
navally dominant, powers like
>> [clears throat]
>> Spain, powers like uh Portugal, powers
like England, etc.
And because of that the Barbary slave
trade eventually wound down. And once
the French conquered Algeria in the
first half of the 19th century, that was
the end of the Barbary slave trade. So
you had millions of Europeans, mainly
women, who were enslaved.
Um what was the number? I'm not sure
about the number. I'm sure you can ask
AI or you can ask you can look it up
what the numbers are. But millions of
Europeans were enslaved
and sold to the Ottomans. The Ottomans
also had very large numbers of African
slaves, African origin slaves.
Um so [clears throat] what happened to
the African origin slaves?
If you had
millions of European slaves
who were sold to the Ottomans.
And you also had
millions of African slaves
who were sold to the Ottomans.
So clearly if you if they're selling
European female slaves to the Ottomans,
the Ottomans, the Turks will obviously
procreate with them.
And the further whiten their population
their offspring, right? They wanted to
become white, a white population. And
that's how they would do it, by either
abducting millions of Greek women
and having children with them, or by
purchasing slave slaves from the Barbary
pirates and having children with them.
So that's how the Turks went from being
a Central Asian race to being a European
race.
Now what about the millions of African
slaves they they had taken?
You see most of these African slaves
were males.
>> [snorts]
>> And what they would do to the male
African slaves is they would castrate
them.
That's what they did.
So the African slaves were used as slave
labor.
And that was it.
None of their genetic genetic traces
survived.
The most horrible
way of exploiting human beings. That's
what the Ottomans did.
And that's the story of the slave trade.
The Ottomans uh
what a brutal, barbaric empire it was.
The Ottoman Empire.
Right, next question. Amisha says, "What
was Kemal Atatürk's involvement and view
of the Armenian genocide? And how
extreme were his views on Turkish
nationalism?"
Mustafa Kemal Atatürk.
He was born Mustafa
in the 19th century. He was born
in a city called Salonica.
It's now called Thessaloniki and it's
part of Greece. Greece was part of the
Ottoman Empire. So that's why
Mustafa Kemal Atatürk Mustafa was born
in
Salonica. It was then called Saloni
Salonica, it's now called Thessaloniki.
His parents were Turkish. I mean his
mother was Albanian, his father his
mother was Zübeyde, his father was Ali
Rıza. He had a sister Makbule.
And he went on to be one of Turkey's
greatest ever
uh soldiers, generals, one of the
greatest generals of all time. Okay?
And um
and he fought he he fought the Turkish
War of Independence.
He was the leader of Turkey in Turkey's
War of Independence from 1919 to 1923.
And it was
a do or die situation. He was fighting
the Ottoman Caliphate. He was also
fighting the European occupying powers
of who had occupied Turkey at the end of
the First World War. And he defeated
them all.
And he won freedom for Turkey.
And his
philosophy, his ideology, his
his vision
was Turkey for the Turks.
Okay?
So Atatürk
in 1915
he was fighting an invasion of Turkey
that had been launched by by Winston
Churchill.
The Dardanelles Campaign, the Gallipoli
Campaign.
And he fought for
months on end, horrific trench warfare,
against all odds, against a superior
enemy. And he defeated them.
And he saved Turkey
from this
Western invasion.
So
that was one of his great deeds. And it
it told you what kind of soldier he was,
one of the greats of all all time.
So 1915 he was fighting
the Westerners.
And his commanding officer in 1915 was
was Liman von Sanders,
a German. Because Turkey was allied with
Germany at the time. And Ger- Germany
was the superior power.
So Atatürk was reporting to a German
commanding officer, Liman von Sanders.
In 1915 you also had the Armenian
genocide happening.
So the Armenian genocide happened in
multiple waves, starting from the second
half of the 19th century.
S- last quarter, maybe, of the 19th
century.
The first wave, then the second wave,
and then 1915 to 19
23 or something, you have the Armenian
genocide.
And the Turks to until today they refuse
to
accept there was a genocide. But
privately they celebrate it.
The Turks.
So 1915, who was in power in Turkey? Was
it Atatürk? No, Atatürk was merely a
soldier.
Who was in power in 1915? It was
the triumvirate
of the Young Turks, who belonged to the
Committee of Union Union and Progress,
the Committee of Union and Progress,
CUP.
It had three leaders who shared power.
The Young Turks, the triumvirate of the
three Pashas.
Enver, Talat, Djemal. Enver Pasha, Talat
Talat Pasha, and Djemal Pasha.
And Talat Pasha was
of Romani origin, but Turkish. Yep.
So the three Pashas. But the Who was the
most powerful of the three Pashas? It
was Enver Pasha.
Let's see what this fine gentleman
looked like, Enver Pasha.
Let's see. Okay, let's see the three
Pashas.
The three pashas, uh Talat, Enver, and
Jamal.
Okay, these three fantastic gentlemen,
and Jamal, Enver. Enver was the most
charismatic of all. He's the guy in
front, obviously, over here.
And the guy on the left, he looks very
Indian because he's a Romani. He is
Talat Pasha.
So, Enver Pasha is the guy who was
you know, the most powerful of the
pashas.
And it was these three pashas who
unleashed the Armenian genocide.
And Atatürk was not involved in that.
He was busy fighting other things. And
obviously, in 1919, you have the Turkish
War of Independence that takes its own
uh course. And at that time, Atatürk was
very busy fighting the caliphate,
the Ottoman caliphate, plus and the
Ottoman caliphate was allied with the
occup- with the Western occupiers,
Britain, France, etc.
And he was fighting them all. So, when
he's fighting the foreign occupiers and
the caliphate, he has no time to kill
Armenians, right? So, essentially, the
the point that I'm trying to make is
that Mustafa Kemal Atatürk was not
involved in the Armenian genocide.
I'm not saying that everything he did
was fantastic. I'm not saying that.
But he was not involved in the Armenian
genocide.
He was definitely involved in the
burning of Smyrna. Have you heard of
this incident ever?
The burning of Smyrna. He was involved
in that.
Maybe he
he
ignored what was happening. But it
happened under his command. Under his
command. It happened by soldiers under
his command.
Maybe he did not pay attention. Maybe he
chose to
ignore what was happening, but
you could say he was responsible for
that.
But he was not responsible for the
Armenian genocide. He did not
participate in that. What were What were
his views about the Armenian genocide?
Privately,
he's said to have
been extremely critical of the genocide.
He said it He said privately that it it
was
a very evil, super criminal act, and
those who did this
should be punished. That was his private
view, maybe semi-public view.
But here's the deal.
Atatürk wanted to create a Turkey for
the Turks.
That means
See,
when Turkey was eventually created out
of all this, there was
a forcible, mandatory population
exchange between Turkey and Greece.
What What What was that?
There were so many
Turkish people in the parts of Greece
that that the
that the nation of Turkey withdrew from.
Those parts of Turkey were part of the
Ottoman Empire, including the Saloniki
where where Atatürk was born. So, you
had lots of Turkish people who lived in
these parts of Greece. And you had many
Greek people who were living in parts of
Turkey and Anatolia because they've been
living there for thousands of years.
There was a forcible population
exchange.
All Turks out of Greece, no mandatory.
And all Greeks out of Turkey, mandatory.
So, Turkey became fully Islamic. Greek
became fully Christian.
It was
done on a mandatory basis.
Right?
>> [clears throat]
>> So,
that ensured that Atatürk got a Turkey
for the Turks.
Now, this new republic he created, the
Republic of Turkey, its identity
and its legitimacy,
it rested
to a large extent on
ensuring continuity
with the territorial outcome and the
demographic outcome of the end of the
Turkish War of Independence, and also on
the demographic outcome of the Armenian
genocide.
Okay?
Because that ensured the creation of a
Turkey for the Turks, which was his
vision anyway.
And that made official recognition of
the
Armenian genocide politically
impossible, politically unacceptable.
And that's why Atatürk publicly stayed
quiet about this.
Okay?
But privately, he's said to have
expressed, you know, deep uh
um disapproval of the Armenian genocide,
and he was definitely not involved in
that. He was definitely not a
participant in this genocide.
Right.
Arhan Sutaria says, "I've been watching
your videos for for 4 years. Thank you
so much. Thank you so much."
Can you explain the changes of the of
dynasties in
the region that's now called Gujarat?
Historically, what dynasties have we had
in Gujarat, right?
Um
Look,
>> [clears throat]
>> See, the Mahajanapada age
starts maybe about
I mean, modern historians will tell you
maybe 500 600 600 maybe 700 BC. Okay? Um
So, before the Mahajanapada period,
you had the late Vedic period,
in which
you know, you would have
Vedic culture
in Gujarat.
You would have the Sindhu Sauvir
dynasty,
which was late, probably post-Vedic, but
before that before that you would have
late Vedic culture in Saurashtra in in
Gujarat, and we're not quite sure what
dynasties were there at the time.
That kind of
is the transition phase between the
so-called Saraswati Sindhu or Harappan
era and the post-Harappan era because
you had a big drought and you know, the
great river dried out and people started
dispersing to various parts of India.
Some went west, some went east, and so
on. And much of that would have happened
through Gujarat.
So, around 600 BC or so, we have the age
of the Mahajanapadas.
And um
Gujarat's various parts of Gujarat may
probably have been part of the Avanti
Mahajanapadas, right?
And uh
that's where you have regional names
within Gujarat like Av- like
Not Avanti.
Anarta, Saurashtra, Lata, etc. Those
names originate in the Mahajanapada
period, and they kind of still persist.
I mean, we still have a part of Gujarat
that's called Saurashtra. We still have
the Lata region of Gujarat, and so on.
Uh so, that's the Mahajanapadas period,
maybe 700 or 600 600 BC. Then about 300
BC, around that time,
you have the rise of the Mauryan Empire.
And we have
Ashokan inscriptions in Gujarat, in
Saurashtra, Girnar. The Girnar mountain,
there is a major inscription of Emperor
Ashok there.
So, that indicates that Gujarat, or at
least Saurashtra, was directly
administered from Pataliputra.
Directly, indirectly, we Gujarat would
have had a regional governor, obviously,
who reported to the emperor in
Pataliputra, but Gujarat was under
Mauryan imperial administration because
the Mauryan Empire
encompassed the whole the essentially
the entirety of the subcontinent. Okay?
So, that is the Mauryan period uh
period.
Then by the 1st century BC, you have
most likely the Shunga dynasty. After
the Shunga dynasty, you have the Kanva
dynasty, which would have ruled Gujarat.
And then there's the transition to maybe
Indo-Greek phase.
It is said that the city of Junagadh was
called Yavana-gadh. So, you you had an
Indo-Greek presence in in Gujarat and
Saurashtra for some time.
And after the Shunga period,
the Kanva period, you would have the
rise of the Mahakshatrapas, the Scythian
rulers, right? It's It's So, you
around
the 1st century BC to to 1st century AD,
you have a transition period, and then
you have the rise of the Western
Satraps, the Mahakshatrapas. Okay?
And the Mahakshatrapas became very
powerful. You had very powerful kings
like Nahapana, like Chastana,
uh who ruled
from this region.
Uh Nahapana, one of his capitals
was possibly Minnanagar, which is
present-day Karachi.
But Karachi is kind of extended Gujarat,
isn't it? Right? Just west of Gujarat,
they have Karachi, Sind Karachi. Uh so,
you had the
the Mahakshatrapas ruled from Gujarat
between
around the 1st century AD
to roughly 3rd 4th centuries AD, and
they were very powerful. They were very
rich, very prosperous because they
controlled the major ports
that were the hubs of trade between
India and the west, whether it is West
Asia, Mesopotamia, whether it is Egypt,
whether it is the Roman Empire, whether
it is whatever else.
So, these ports were were
very very uh
critical to India's trade with
the Western world, essentially.
And the Mahakshatrapas controlled these
ports because these ports were in
Gujarat and Saurashtra.
So, you have the Mahakshatrapa era,
okay? In the 1st to 3rd 4th century AD.
Then from the 4th century AD to the 5th
6th century AD, you have the Gupta
Empire, which rules Gujarat, which rules
India, the subcontinent. The Gupta
Empire
defeated the Mahakshatrapas,
and
you could say took over Gujarat and took
possession of the great ports.
So, that obviously you is is an if
you're an empire, you need to control
the ports where all the money comes
from. So, the Guptas took over and you
have Gupta rule over Gujarat between the
4th to maybe 6th century
uh AD.
And then the Gupta Gupta empire also
after a century and a half or so it
starts uh declining and then the
regional empires become regional chiefs
and then you have the Maitraka dynasty
which ruled out of Vallabhi in
Saurashtra.
So, it's a major kingdom but it's not an
empire, it's a dynasty, the Maitraka
dynasty.
And after the Maitraka dynasty
you have a period where you have
Gurjara-Pratihara and Rashtrakutas and
Gujarat is kind of fragmented and you
have the rise of the Chavda dynasty
around the 7th century AD or something
like that.
And that rules for about two and a half
centuries. The major ruler was Vanaraja
Chavda who
uh ruled out of
Anhilpur Anhilpur Patan which is in
northern Gujarat.
And it is during this time that Gujarat
acquires a distinct
cultural identity from the rest of from
from other uh parts of western India.
Then after the decline of the Chavda
dynasty you have the Solanki dynasty
that comes up and the first king of the
Solanki dynasty was a nephew of the last
Chavda king.
So, the Solanki dynasty
uh becomes a very powerful kingdom which
is again based out of the same capital
that the Chavdas founded, Anhilpur
Patan.
After So, the Chavda dynasty ends in the
late 900s AD.
And then you have the Solanki dynasty
which rules for another maybe
what? Two and a half centuries or so.
Um
And in the 13th century you have the
Vaghela dynasty which was the last major
Rajput dynasty after the Chavdas and the
Solankis to rule Gujarat. And after that
um maybe the early 15th century you have
um
Gujarat coming under
the Delhi Sultanate.
So, Gujarat becomes a
province under the Delhi Sultanate and
there are there's a governor appointed
by the Delhi Sultans in Gujarat.
And then
the Delhi Sultanate crumbles.
Uh and in the 15th century Gujarat
becomes a an independent Sultanate uh
under Muzaffar Shah or something his
name was. Okay, that foreign Turkic
ruler who ruled
part of Gujarat for
and and his descendants. So, from the
15th to the late 16th century you have
uh
a Sultanate of Gujarat.
And then from the 16th century all the
way to the early 18th century you have
the Mughal empire.
So, Gujarat becomes a subah.
And uh one of the major
the it had major ports like
Khambat
and Surat.
Right?
And the the Mughal empire rules uh
Gujarat.
Then uh from the 1700s
to the early 19th century you have
Maratha rule. So, the Marathas liberated
India
including Gujarat from the Turks. And
you have the Peshwas, the Gaekwads, etc.
who uh
liberate India from the Mughals. And you
have a Gaekwad state in Vadodara in
Baroda.
So, that's between the 1700s to the
early 19th century.
And then you have the British East India
Company. The British East India Company
established a trading post, a factory in
Surat in the 1600s.
Very early 1600s.
And uh
they eventually by the 19th century they
take over, you know.
So, then Gujarat comes under the British
East India Company and eventually
the Crown of England.
And that was that's about it. So, that's
kind of
the chronology of the various rulers who
have ruled Gujarat, the various
dynasties and rulers
um
and lineages that have ruled Gujarat
for the past about 3,000 years.
All right.
Shub says, "Could there be a possibility
that Native American and Native
Australian civilizations were as
advanced as Indian civilization? Do we
have any evidence? Are whites still till
date successful in hiding the evidence?"
Look,
when it comes to Australia, there is no
evidence
of an advanced civilization.
What are the
the telltale signs that an advanced
civilization will leave behind in the
archaeological record?
You will
see cities, a network of cities
in the archaeological record.
You will see large buildings. You will
see sophisticated
buildings and great structures, etc.
in a city in the archaeo- archaeological
archaeological record. You will see
evidence of large population centers.
You will see evidence of large-scale
agriculture. You will see evidence of
literature. You will see evidence of
astronomy and science and technology.
These are the signs and symptoms
that an advanced civilization leaves
behind in the archaeological record even
if it is destroyed.
Now, there is no such thing in
Australia.
No such thing as far as we know.
So, to the best of our understanding,
there was never an advanced Native
Australian civilization in Australia.
It doesn't mean that it's a they're
backward, primitive, they're bad, they
deserve to be conquered, none of that.
They had a certain way of living.
It doesn't mean that they deserve to be
conquered.
It doesn't mean that others it gives
others the right to conquer them and and
brutalize and and genocide them. But
that's how it was for the Native
Australians. They never became an
advanced civilization comparable to
let's say India.
What about the Native Americans?
Well, the Native Americans were
definitely way more advanced.
Possibly more advanced than the
Europeans. The only thing they were less
advanced than the Europeans in
was the systemic systematic application
of violence. The Europeans were better
than the than the Native Americans at
that. But when it comes to uh
Central America, Mesoamerica, South
America, you had very advanced
civilizations. You had civilizations
with millions of people living there.
With incredible architecture.
They had incredible technology. They had
calendar systems.
They had calendars that could predict
predict events
thousands of years in the future.
>> [clears throat]
>> Um the Mesoamericans possibly
independently discovered zero
independently from us Indians. Right?
And so much more. So, the Native
American populations from Mesoamerica
which is Mexico, Panama, that region.
And Latin America, South America, the uh
Inca empire
Peru, etc.
Very advanced, very advanced, very
prosperous, very high um
uh so level of sophistication of
technology, scientific advancements um
high quality governance
great logistical capabilities
>> [snorts]
>> great administration, all of that was
there.
Uh when it comes to North America
in North America, United States and
Canada.
You know, they don't allow
archaeological
work on Native American history.
There are
I mean, see in in Mesoamerica, Mexico,
in South America, you have these major
monumental architectural works like
pyramids, etc.
They
they're unmistakable. There are such
things in North America also but these
are suppressed, they are hidden away.
Those have been destroyed, bulldozed,
etc.
There is evidence of large-scale cities
even in North America in what is now the
United States.
But you will not see anyone highlighting
those things. Those things are quietly
brushed under the carpet.
So, in the United States and in Canada
they've been very good at suppressing
the evidence or destroying the evidence
willfully.
So,
the gist of the answer is that Native
American
civilizations were pretty advanced.
Pretty sophisticated.
High
uh technology for that for that time
period. Very good governance, very good
administration.
Um
great advances in science, technology,
literature, poetry, so much more.
>> [clears throat]
>> And uh yeah, but not Australia. Right?
So, that's how it was.
Amisha says, "How did Native American
society not completely collapse from
losing 90% of their people to smallpox?"
So, we are taught or told that, you
know, yeah, unfortunately the Native
American society
in various parts of the Americas,
[snorts] whether it's North America,
Mesoamerica, South America, whatever,
90% plus of their populations died out.
And it was very unfortunate because of
smallpox. That's it's because of
smallpox and diseases.
That's what we are told.
There's no question that diseases, old
world diseases, Eurasian diseases played
a major role in the decimation of the
populations.
But the 90% figure which
could be
>> [clears throat]
>> an underrepresentation of what happened.
Maybe it's 95%.
Maybe 50% was diseases.
And the rest was genocide.
So, it's not like, you know, the
Europeans came and sat there and the
natives started dying out.
No, the Europeans actively killed them
off
as many as they could.
Right?
So,
I mean, look at the story of what
happened to Hispaniola.
The island which is now half Haiti, half
Dominican Republic.
Christopher Columbus became the governor
general. He was given the title of
governor general of this island by the
Spanish crown.
And at the time there were millions of
Native American people who lived there.
Within 20-30 years,
zero.
Okay?
And there was this this priest
Bartolomé de las Casas
who observed this
firsthand in front of his own eyes and
he wrote about this.
He was an advocate of not killing Native
Americans. Merely convert them to
Christianity. Don't don't kill them.
And he was very critical of what
Christopher Columbus and later governors
did to the people.
And that's just one example.
>> [clears throat and cough]
>> This happened over and over and over
again. So and the the the people, the
Arawak people of Hispaniola
were did not die of smallpox. They died
of genocide.
And the same happened over and over
again. So the 90% figure
could be accurate. Maybe it is still an
underrepresentation. Maybe it's 95%.
But
some portion of it was due due to
disease, the rest of it was due to
genocide. And nobody can deny that.
Now and what was the death toll in in
numbers? Maybe 100 million. Between 50
to 100 million. That is a shocking
number.
Now how did Native American society not
completely collapse? They wanted to
survive somehow.
So we have small population groups
that still exist in North America.
In reservations, etc.
These reservations were meant to be
temporary.
And
they still regard Native Americans as as
a problem.
They just want Native Americans to
either assimilated assimilate out
assimilate into the white population and
stop being Native American so that the
land can be taken, the reservations, the
land the substantial land is there. Or
maybe they should just die out. And then
once again the whites can take the land.
So the white settlers are still waiting
for the Native Americans to die out. The
Native Americans are simply a minor
substratum subclass of
of
society in the Americas.
In a super marginalized
substratum of society.
They Obviously everybody wants to
survive. They want to keep things going.
They want to
continue living and continue passing on
their culture to whatever extent they
can.
And they're trying to do that.
Right?
So
the whites were not able to exterminate
them completely and that's why they
still survive.
They have tried to be resilient.
But today, you know, most Native
Americans
if you look at them, they don't even
look Native American anymore. They don't
have brown skin.
Many of them have blonde hair, blue
eyes. They've married into the European
communities and
most of them don't even look Native
American.
So they're slowly losing their identity.
Their their their
separate distinct
ethnicity
it's it's being eroded
generation after generation.
And it's the the society is collapsing.
Most of them
have been made to convert to
Christianity. Their religion is gone.
Their their
their belief system, their culture is
gone. And slowly the even the languages
are gone. The Native American languages.
Hardly anybody speaks Native American
languages now, even on the reservations.
Most people I would say speak English.
So it's it's being eroded step by step,
generation by generation and the
eventual objective is to erase the
identity
of the Native Americans and just
once that happens, you can take over all
the land. There you have it.
Swapnil says, "Why were British redcoats
so widely disliked by American colonists
during the years leading up to the
American Revolution?" Who were the
British redcoats? What did they What is
What do you mean by redcoat? Let's see.
It's the distinct red uniform. Okay?
I'm sure everybody is familiar with this
red uniform. You even had these red
uniformed guys
in India
during the British occupation of India.
Eventually it became khaki, but
originally
it was red. So you had these redcoats,
these red uniformed soldiers who
occupied
um North America with the the region
that would eventually become the United
States. Okay?
So why were these British redcoats so
widely despised in in uh
by American colonists during the years
leading up to the American Revolution or
the American War of Independence? The
American War of Independence is from
1775 to 1783.
Okay?
So the years leading up to that is from
the 1760s onwards, let's say.
So before the 1760s, you see uh there
were historically
from the beginning of the British
attempts to occupy
North America.
The British never sent a standing army
to North America. Starting from
Jamestown, starting from Plymouth.
They never sent a standing army. They
sent colonists in large numbers. Many of
them died out. Jamestown was a disaster.
Roanoke is a mystery and a disaster.
Plymouth kind of succeeded. And the
Americans want to forget about Jamestown
because of
the way things went there. Cannibalism,
barbarism, what not.
>> [clears throat]
>> But eventually the Americans succeeded.
And the Americans had a very different
strategy from the Spaniards. The
Spaniards were looking for gold.
They were looking for slaves and
conversions. The Americans were looking
for land.
Which is why the natives were genocided.
The the English were looking for land.
So they took over the land, they took
over the land. And eventually you had a
substantial uh population of English
people in eastern in the eastern United
States on the east coast of the United
States.
And it's then the 1960s that the
British crown sends the redcoats
to the colonies.
The redcoats are a standing army. So
suddenly
the colonists who have grabbed all this
land and who are like living
happily suddenly find this army looming
over them sent from across the Atlantic
Ocean thousands of kilometers away.
Right?
So that gave them the sense of being
under occupation
by England.
And England London became this
this this
it became
the center of tyranny
to the colonies.
So it's like the British crown no longer
trusted the English colonists.
It regarded them as as as people who are
potential traitors and potential
whatever.
And
they now need to be controlled by force
and by and through tyranny. Right? So
that's in the 1760s that the redcoats
were sent to the colonies. And not only
that, okay? So you the
England
sends an army
to the Americas and then it puts the
financial burden on the colonies.
Okay?
So the English crown, the English
parliament
it required that the colonial
communities had to provide housing
to the redcoats, to the occupying
soldiers. They had to provide food to
the occupying soldiers and to they had
to provide all other necessary and
required supplies to the occupying
soldiers, the redcoats.
Right? So not only are the colonies by
being occupied by England, but the
colonies have to pay for the occupation.
Right? The entire cost of
the occupation is now shifted on the
colonies.
And um
you see
there are all these taxes that were
being imposed on the colonies by the
English crown.
And the redcoats were now seen as the
enforcers of these
of these loathsome taxes.
So the colonies had no representation in
parliament, but they were being taxed.
And they said that there should be no
taxation without representation.
But the redcoats were now enforcing this
And then there was
social friction.
There was job competition. You see these
redcoats, they were on the payroll of
the British crown.
But many of these redcoat soldiers, they
would also take off-duty work as
laborers
as as as dock workers in the dockyards
and they would compete with the local
with the local men.
They would compete with them in a
limited job market. That created
problems for the local people
population.
Job social friction.
And
there's another factor. See these uh
redcoats, they were typically recruited
from
England's poorest people, poorest
classes.
And they had a reputation which may have
been justified, possibly would have been
justified, that they had a tendency for
drunkenness, they had a tendency for
thievery theft
and violence.
Okay?
So the redcoats were regarded as as
dangerous, as morally suspect people, as
thieves, as violent people, as as people
prone to drunkenness.
And then they were competing for jobs
and they were enforcing oppressive laws
and oppressive taxes
and and so on. And uh
and
So
these are the reasons
why the British redcoats were so widely
disliked, despised by the American
colonists in the years leading up to the
American Revolution and in I think it
was sometime probably
the American War of Independence starts
in 1775 and it lasts about 8 years until
1783.
In a few years before that I think it
was 1770 or something there was a
massacre in Boston
in which these red coats fired upon
protesters.
Boston, Massachusetts.
The Boston Massacre was again
perpetrated by these red coats.
Maybe like it's not like 300 people died
in that, maybe five, eight, 10 people
may have died in the Boston Massacre,
but it was reported widely as a massacre
of lots of people and that added to the
ire to the to the
you know antipathy that the locals had
towards the red coats. So because of all
these factors the British red coats were
very widely disliked despised by the
American colonists
in the years leading up to the American
Revolution and then the red coats fought
the American
independence fighters and yeah.
>> [clears throat and cough]
>> Amisha says,
"How common was it for white female
slave owners to have relationships with
their slaves in the antebellum American
South?"
We're talking about pre-1860s,
right? The antebellum
period means the period before the
American Civil War.
The American Civil War is what? 1860, 61
around that time? 63? When did the
American Civil War begin? Let's let's
quickly fact check.
American Civil see Civil War.
When does it begin? 1861, that's right.
I was right. Then it lasts about four,
five years until 1865.
So the antebellum period is the period
before the Civil War begins
and
that could date back five years, 10
years, 100 years, whatever. Antebellum
South. South means the southern part of
the United States which was pro-slavery.
And the northern part of the United
States eventually became anti-slavery
because they adopted embraced new
technology that made slavery
unnecessary. You know, advanced
technology that
which ensure you don't you don't need
slaves. Like today you have soldiers in
the military, but when with the advent
of robots and drones you won't need
soldiers potentially.
A similar so if you adopt new technology
uh some jobs go out of
you know, they're no longer required. So
that's what happened in the north, but
in the south they wanted to continue
slavery and that's why you had the Civil
War.
So you had the system of plantation
slavery etc. in the American South.
And it was very common for slave for
slave owners males
to sexually abuse their female Africans
African origin slaves. It was pretty
common and plenty of uh
slave women gave birth to children of
their white owners that sort of thing
and those children were typically
regarded as slaves and that's how it
would go. And you see
the male
slave owners who would do this to the
female slaves
they did not have to take any
responsibility.
They could simply disregard the fact
that there are now half white half black
children
that these uh black slave uh
persons female persons have ladies have.
They could just disregard that, you
know. So the males
in in in
that male-dominated Christian
uh milieu
of the antebellum South male
white males did not have any you don't
have to take responsibility for any of
these things.
But the greatest of all taboos
was for a white woman
to have a child with a black slave. That
was the greatest taboo.
And there were all kinds of harsh laws
against that.
So if a white woman
gave birth to a child with a black man
who was typically a slave black people
were slaves.
So if a white woman gave birth to a
child whose father was a black slave she
would be enslaved
and the child would the child would be
enslaved.
The child would be born a slave and the
woman would be in some states it was she
would be enslaved for five years some
some years in slums in some states she
would be a slave as long as the man was
alive.
That sort of thing.
Um
>> [clears throat]
>> So it was very very um
harshly frowned upon. It was a great
taboo.
Uh women
could not escape responsibility.
Men
always evaded responsibility in um
that society.
So it was pretty uncommon for white
female slave owners to have
relationships with their slaves. It did
happen. There are some records of that
happening
um and
it the incidence was very low among
white female slave owners, but it was
kind of slightly higher
among
poor white females
who were not land owners or slave
owners.
So among those women the incidence of
having um
children with with slaves was slightly
higher I would say.
But it was a great taboo and uh
it carried a huge social stigma. So it
was not very common. Did happen. There
are some recorded incidents etc., but
overall it was extremely uncommon and it
was a great social taboo.
Okay.
Let's take a couple more questions. We
already crossed two hours. Nirvana Shang
says, "One rarely hears about the
Somalia affair of the early 1990s when
Canadian forces were implicated in
serious abuses during their peacekeeping
mission in Somalia.
What were the underlying objectives of
Canada's involvement in Somalia and to
what extent were the incidents the
result of systemic issues within the
military versus emotional or
disciplinary breakdowns among individual
soldiers? Thank you for your attention
to this part." Okay, look Canada if you
see
the record the track record of Canadian
soldiers during the Second World War
it's not very nice.
It's not very nice.
Okay.
Now that's the Second World War 1940s
we're talking about.
Now coming to the 1990s
there was
you know, a UN intervention in Somalia
in the early 1990s. You had this uh
ruler of Somalia called Siad Barre
who was ousted and then you had a period
of anarchy chaos in Somalia.
Um Mogadishu was the capital here. You
had the Mohamed Farrah Aidid who
fought the Americans a long story there,
but Somalia was in chaos.
No real government all kinds of factions
fighting each other
whatever food supplies etc. the UN would
give
all each faction would capture that and
hold it
to ransom
from the people unless they were given
money or whatever and that sort of
thing. It was it was a terrible
catastrophe and that's why you had
a US-led UN peacekeeping intervention in
Somalia.
And the Canadians participated in that.
So that was the thing.
And this Somalia affair is in 1993.
And this was a series of uh
brutal
human rights abuses by Canadian
soldiers.
So I
I can think of at least two incidents.
You see the the Canadian soldiers
Canadian um troops would have these army
camps etc.
and the Somalian
population was starved. It was starving.
They were always on the lookout for food
and there was food in the UN camp. The
Somalians would you know kids etc. they
would sometimes teenagers sometimes come
in you know
scrounge around for food and try to get
some food.
And the Canadians started looking upon
these Somalians as potential saboteurs
and there was an incident in which the
Canadian soldiers multiple Canadian
soldiers shot a boy
a young
male
and it looked like
that boy was shot.
I mean there was no need to kill him it
looked like him. I mean his body was so
badly damaged it could not be taken in
one piece back to the camp or whatever
it was. It had to be put in a body bag
or something
and medical examination showed that the
kid was probably
shot in the head a few minutes after he
was shot in other places or parts of the
body that sort of thing.
So clear human rights abuse by Canadian
soldiers and then you had another
another incident
in which another Somalian teenager
once again a male
was essentially kidnapped by the
Canadians under whatever pretext maybe
he's a saboteur maybe he's a thief
whatever the
excuse they made up
and they kidnapped this boy and then
they slowly tortured him to death.
And it's like
maybe two, three soldiers involved in
the torturing of this boy to death
including sexual abuse.
But
dozens of Canadian soldiers saw this
happening.
And they were okay okay with it. Doesn't
matter. And some of them took
photographs and those photographs
unfortunately are still
potentially available on the internet.
That boy being tortured to death in all
kinds of brutal ways.
So the Americans what they did in Abu
Ghraib
in [snorts] Baghdad after their invasion
and occupation of Iraq
the kind of atrocities they did to the
Iraqi civilians in Abu Ghraib prison the
Somalia affair
of the 1990s of 1993
was done by Canadians. It's it's a
smaller scale
example of what the Americans would do
later.
So that's the Somalia affair of the
early 1990s and uh
and it is said that this this Canadian
detachment regiment whatever it was I
don't know what the division or regiment
name was. I don't remember that. You can
look it up if you want.
It was said to be highly racist.
Some of the soldiers were big fans of
the
the Nazi Führer,
Adolf Hitler.
Some of them were apparently members of
the Ku Klux Ku Klux Klan. Some of them
had Confederate flags with that is, you
know, the Confederate
United States was the Southern United
States that supported slavery.
They were super racist. So, it was a
systemic issue. It was not
um emotional or disciplinary breakdown
of any kind. And later on the various
Canadian scientists, doctors tried to
claim that these soldiers had been
administered some anti-malaria drug that
made them prone to not having full
control over their behavior. That was
the kind of uh
justification that was given.
And most of these individuals who were
involved in these human rights abuses
were given very light punishments.
They should you know
They should have been given very harsh
punishments. They were given very light
punishments. Maybe a dishonorable
discharge from the military. Maybe like
5 days in jail or 30 days in jail. Light
not not
maximum security or whatever. And
essentially everybody got off basically
scot-free.
And that was the deal.
So, that's the Somalia affair. If you
want you can look it up. It's not very
pleasant reading. I assure you of that.
Nirvana Shang says, "Who What explains
the persistence of starlight tours in
Canada? And how did authorities justify
or ignore the practice?"
Starlight tours. Sounds very pleasant.
Starlight tour. What's a starlight tour?
It's something that's said to
be a practice
in the Canadian province of
Saskatchewan.
The capital of Saskatchewan is
Saskatoon. Would you like to see the
map? I'll show you the map. All right,
here we go.
Where is map? We shall find the
Saskatchewan.
So, we are going to North America. We're
going to Canada.
In Canada you can see this SKO here.
Pretty large province, right? North of
Montana and North Dakota.
Dakota.
Saskatchewan.
And the capital of Saskatchewan
is Saskatoon.
Excuse me.
So,
if you
take a look at the coordinates, it's
pretty high up north.
Okay?
And it gets pretty cold in winter.
Pretty cold in winter.
The temperatures in the Saskatoon region
in the Saskatchewan region
uh drop to minus 20s the minus 20s
degrees Celsius. Sometimes even minus
30s. Minus 30 31 32 whatever.
Okay?
And there's a lot of Native American
people who live in this region.
>> [clears throat]
>> So, the Canadian poli- police, the Royal
Canadian Mounted Police RCMP, and
Saskatoon Police, and Saskatchewan
Police, they have this
charming practice.
What they do
is that they will
catch some Native American
person.
Typically somebody who has had a drink
or two.
They will accuse the person of
drunkenness.
Put that person in a
police vehicle in the evening.
Drive them out of the city a few
kilometers.
And leave them in the night out there.
When the temperature goes to minus
25 minus 30 degrees.
So, what happens? That person will
freeze to death.
And that practice has been
known to happen
since at least the 1970s. I'm sure it's
had a I'm sure it's got a
great history that must have
that must go back to the what
several centuries. But it's known to
have been
a thing since at least the 1970s.
And there are
several examples several names that are
known of of Native American people who
were
taken for a starlight tour in this
manner
uh by the Canadian police. And uh
Yeah, so that's what a starlight tour
is. And has any action been taken
against the police? Not really. Nothing
serious. Nothing much.
Uh do authorities justify this? They
don't justify it.
For the longest time they tried to deny
it ever exists. Now they say that yeah,
we're looking into it blah blah blah.
Uh do they ignore the practice? They're
trying their best to ignore it and to
brush it under the carpet.
Now, what explains this?
Why do the Canadian police
have this practice of taking innocent
people, Native people,
and throwing them out into the open
in the night in winter
several kilometers away from a city
where you can't reach the city before
you freeze to death?
Why do they do that?
Because the
North American settlers
are descendants of mainly
Englishmen.
And the English
did not come to North America looking
for gold or treasure. They came looking
for land.
And if you want land, you want to clear
the land
of whatever existed on the land.
So, if you're a farmer and you want to
have a
plantation.
And if there are let's say
some animals on the land who eat your
crops, you want to
you will treat them as pests and you
will want to exterminate them.
Similarly,
the English
sought to exterminate the natives.
And that
approach, that attitude
that desire still persists.
The natives are regarded as pests.
In Australia, the natives were regarded
were classified as flora and fauna.
Fauna mainly which means animals not
humans.
And that was used to justify their
extermination. In Tasmania the natives
were entirely exterminated.
And today in Australia the natives are
they barely exist.
And in Australia which which people is
it? It's the English. Isn't it?
In the US and Canada again it's the
English. So, they have had the same
attitude towards land.
So,
the natives are seen as a nuisance. They
are seen as an inconvenience.
And the sooner the natives
cease to exist the better it will be for
the English so that they can take over
all the land.
And that's how it is. So, it's racism.
It's a continuation of a desire to
genocide the natives.
And uh yeah.
That's what explains the persistence of
the starlight tours.
It's the fact that the natives are
second class citizens. They are barely
regarded as citizens and
>> [clears throat]
>> they are treated the way the Romani are
treated in Europe.
Right? So, that's why these starlight
tours
uh persist.
Okay, we've crossed over 16 minutes. I
still have a bunch of questions I've
selected, but I won't be able to take
those today. So, let me see now if there
are any questions in the live chat.
And I can see there are 16 super chats,
which means I'm going to have a long uh
Okay, let's see. Let's go to the super
chats. Please don't take more super
chats so that I can end this reasonably
on time. It's already over time, but
okay.
So, VSVS
has another question. Namaste, sir.
Well, namaste back to you. Thank you so
much
for your contribution to the channel.
Thank you so much.
Um okay, next question is once again by
VSVS. It's a question by Al Janib. "Why
only British East India Company
succeeded far more than other East India
companies in capturing India?"
Because the British East In- East India
Company was
better at not only the systematic
application of violence.
They had better better administration.
They understood the control of trade
routes better
than the other East India companies.
Then overall,
they essentially were like
merchants with an army.
See, the Spanish,
the Portuguese, the English, the French,
the Dutch, the the the Danes, they all
tried to colonize various parts of the
world.
And when it comes to the subcontinent
and beyond, the overall region,
you had
the British obviously who had an East
India Company. You had uh
the Portuguese
who tried to colonize India. You had the
French who tried to colonize India. The
Dutch tried to colonize India to a
little extent. The Danes also had a
presence. The Dutch colonized the East
Indies, which is Indonesia, that region.
And they all had different approaches.
So, when it comes to the Portuguese,
they wanted
to control only
coastal ports.
They did not want to invest in
territorial acquisitions and
administering territories.
They only wanted to control coastal
cities and ports. They invested in
fortified ports.
And they spread their entire investment
across these ports, this network of
ports, and the control of the attempt to
control trade routes. And the Portuguese
were funded by the crown.
So, the only source of funding was the
crown.
And similar for other powers, but
the English
>> [clears throat]
>> they were not con- they were not
uh
first of all, they They not funded by
the crown. They were funded by
investors.
The East India Company was a joint stock
company. A bunch of investors come
together,
pool their resources, their money,
take shares, and they finance
continually
the operations of the of the East India
Company. And the East India Company did
not have the same strategy as the
Portuguese. They did not simply merely
invest in fortified
ports.
They invested in territorial
acquisitions and governing territories.
So, their entire strategy was different.
It was better. It was superior.
And it is something that you should
study to understand how power works and
how
a small nation can take over a large
large civilization. All right?
>> [clears throat]
>> Abhirup Abhirup Sarkar, thank you very
much, sir. Thank you.
Sumer Singh says, "I'm asking a
out of topic question."
Enemies of the RRR movie can try to
derail the second part by having the
original print leaked before release.
How do makers prevent the thing? How do
makers prevent the thing? By not leaking
it. By having tight security, tight
control.
Right?
If you have lax security,
it's going to be a problem.
So, ensure it doesn't get leaked out.
And that's difficult because even
Hollywood movies get leaked out before
they are released sometimes.
So, they're going to have to be very
careful about this, okay? All right.
>> [clears throat]
>> Abhirup Sarkar says,
"Is J.B. J.B. Morgan and other banks the
current US deep state? They loaned war
They loaned for the First World War and
the Second World War and were pivotal in
handling war weapons." They did not ever
handle war weapons, sir. They financed
the the sale and purchase of war of of
weapons in wars.
I'll see. Banks are instruments of the
deep state.
The deep state,
let's say it hypothetically exists, it
needs to control various aspects of
[snorts] the world order, the financial
system,
the trade routes,
key nations.
They have to invest in penetrating, like
they say, penetrating the cabinets of
key nations,
et cetera. So, one of the key aspects of
global control is control of the
financial system.
And to control the financial system, you
have to control key countries, key
nations, like the UK,
where you have London, which is a key
financial,
uh, you know, capital
of the world.
And you have to control the key banks.
You have to control banks, major banks
within nations.
You have to control major financial
international financial institutions,
like,
for example, the World Bank, the
International Monetary Fund. You have to
control, uh, systems like the SWIFT
system, and so on. So, the point is,
these banks
are
one element
of what the deep state controls. They
are not the deep state. They are
instruments
of the deep state, if the deep state
exists. All right?
Okay. And people are taking more super
chats now.
>> [laughter]
>> Why Heydrich was lucky mascot for
Hitler? What is Heydrich?
What's Heydrich? I'm not sure what
Heydrich is. Let me see. Let me Google
it. I seem to be super ignorant about
what this Heydrich war is or was.
Heydrich.
What's Heydrich?
Heydrich, Reinhard Heydrich.
Um, I have not studied the life story of
this,
uh, individual, so I won't be able to
tell you. Sorry.
Uh,
assassinated in Prague, Czechia.
Reinhard Tristan Eugen Heydrich was a
high was a German high-ranking SS and
police official in Nazi Germany.
One of the principal architects of the
Holocaust. He held the rank of
SS-Obergruppenführer
und General der Polizei.
Many generals Many historians regard
Heydrich, uh, as one of the most
sinister figures within Nazi regime.
Okay. I have not studied this
gentleman's this this individual's, um,
life history, so I can't say. Sorry.
VSVS says, "Question by AMF." Okay, we
are now piling on the super chats. Are
we?
India was under occupation for 1,000
years. Do you think Indian traders
played major role? Look, every nation,
like I have said in the past,
every nation has traitors.
It's not like we are special and we are
we produce the highest number of traders
per capita in the world. No.
Every nation has a certain percentage of
the population that has traitorous
instincts.
Now, when you are a nation under
distress, under foreign occupation,
then it will look like there are more
traitors than than usual because the
traitors become useful then to the
foreigners, the occupants. But if you're
a powerful nation that is super
sovereign and you're not under foreign
occupation, the traitors become
invisible because they are powerless.
They have nobody to serve.
So, when a nation is facing major
misfortunes, it's under foreign
occupation, that's when it looks like
there are way more traitors. Let me tell
you something about the United States,
okay?
Have you heard of the year of the spy?
Spy. Year of the spy.
1985, the year of the spy. Uh, Zoom
back.
A period when numerous high-profile
espionage cases, including
involving Soviet spies
in the United States, okay?
John Walker Jr. family spy ring.
Uh, let me Okay.
John Anthony Walker.
Richard Kelly Smith,
>> [snorts]
>> who was a physicist. Oh, man.
Sharon Scranage. Larry Wu-Tai Chin.
>> [clears throat]
>> Jonathan Jay Pollard. Ronald William
Pelton. Randy Miles Jeffries. Edward Lee
Howard. And so many more.
Doesn't it look like the US has more
spies per capita than than India? So,
understand this, please. Let us put
things in the right context, in the
global context.
Then you'll understand
that it's not like we had we are a
nation that produces lots of traitors.
Yeah, and when you're under foreign
occupation, you will have foreign
collaborators.
You'll have that.
So, what you need is a strong government
government that identifies and
deals with the traitors appropriately.
Then,
once you have that, it will look like
there are no traitors in this country.
It's a super fine country. It's never
the case. There's always a certain
percentage of any population
that is going to have criminal
tendencies. And there's always going to
be a certain percentage of any
population that's going to have
treasonous tendencies. So, it's not
something special to and something that
is like
exclusive to India.
VSVS says, "Question by Real Painter. A
discovery shows that the people in the
IVC also had blue eye phenotype. How is
this possible?" There are people in
India today who have blue eyes.
Yeah, there are people in India today
who have blue I have met people who are
Indian
who I have met a couple of people who
have red hair.
Irish kind of hair. Not albino people,
regular people, but red hair.
I have met people who have blue eyes. I
have met people who have green eyes. We
have all the phenotypes in India. Why is
it not not possible?
We
in the Indian subcontinent,
the population that we have, all people,
they have the highest
genetic diversity outside of Africa.
That's because India was the place where
you had
the first proper settlement of the out
of Africa migration, the those people.
So, all the phenotypes are going to be
present in India.
You know, green eyes, blue eyes, gray
eyes,
brown eyes, as as I have, uh, blonde
hair, red hair, whatever else hair,
everything. White skin, black skin,
brown skin, various shades of white and
whatever. Every phenotype is going to be
found in India, in the subcontinent.
Okay, Diva uh,
Diva is a new member. Well, Diva, um,
Diana K. Aviva,
thank you very much and welcome to the
channel's membership. Thank you very
much.
Godliness says, "Can you explain the
history of terrorism? Every expert have
their own narrative on this. For you,
historically, when did when did
terrorism start and by whom?"
Now,
that is very controversial.
It's a very controversial question.
Uh, when did terrorism start? Look,
terrorism started What First of all,
let's define terrorism.
What is the difference between warfare
and terrorism?
See, warfare is
when,
let's say you have two nations or two
kingdoms, two empires that are fighting.
Warfare is when a professional army
fights against another professional
army. The soldiers fight the soldiers,
and that's warfare.
The objective is to defeat the
adversary nation, adversary kingdom, or
empires' military,
and thereby achieve your political and
military objectives. Your military
objectives will be to defeat the
military, to capture territory, maybe.
And your political objective may be to
effect a regime change. So, that is
warfare.
Now, what is terrorism?
Terrorism is when you don't fight the
adversary's military, you attack their
innocent, unarmed civilians. That is
terrorism. That's the difference between
warfare and terrorism.
When did terrorism start?
Terrorism started whenever
you had
a
a kingdom or or a culture that decided
that it's okay to harm civilians,
to attack civilians, to enslave
civilians, civilians to
do whatever atrocities are done to
civilians.
See, historically in the subcontinent,
it would be armies fighting armies. You
would have one or two bad rotten apples
in a few thousand years, like Kansa
Mama,
like Jarasandha,
you know, like Dhanananda. Some evil
kings were there, but overall
when two kingdoms fought each other, it
would be the army fighting the army.
They would never touch civilians.
Terrorism started when
you had armies starting to
attack civilians.
That is terrorism. So, whenever that
started is when terrorism started. I
will not go beyond that.
VSVS says, "Sorry for going off topic,
but Sir Cena is retiring tomorrow match
at 6:30 live." You mean John Cena?
Well, he's been fighting since before I
was born, right? Well, he's finally
retiring. Okay.
Uh Chirag Chirag says, "Hello, sir. Was
Germany under Kaiser Wilhelm II overly
confident in its ability to defeat
France, Britain, and Russia, leading it
to ally with the Austro-Hungarian Empire
despite the risks?" See, unless you are
confident, you won't take such actions,
right?
The First World War was so incredibly
complicated, convoluted.
If you ask me right now, I don't exactly
remember
>> [laughter]
>> the cause and effect chain, who It
starts with the Balkan Wars.
That's before the First World War
starts.
Then you you have um
the assassination of Archduke
Yeah, Ferdinand. And then
in a matter of days, all the dominoes
fall into space into into place. So,
Germany
allied with the Austro-Hungarian Empire.
Serbia was allied with
Russia.
And France, Italy, it's super
complicated. But yes, overall Germany
was pretty confident that it's going to
it's going to
you know, defeat
France, Britain, Russia. And France,
Britain, Russia was a very unlikely
alliance, actually, wasn't it?
Yeah, so
they were confident and they their
confidence was clearly misplaced. The
Austro-Hungarian Empire collapsed and
disintegrated completely.
And Germany was humiliated, Treaty of
Versailles, which was eventually the
cause of the Second World War.
Chirag Chirag says, "Perestroika and
Glasnost. Ah, Mikhail Gorbachev, 1980s.
Perestroika and Glasnost were
fundamentally well-intentioned reforms.
How did they affect the Soviet Union and
or Russia, and why did they ultimately
contribute to instability rather than
renewal?"
See, it wasn't Perestroika. And what is
Perestroika? What's Glasnost? It's
openness, it's transparency. The USSR
had this historical tendency to keep
everything suppressed, to to be opaque,
to suppress information, to
it had this, you know,
reputation for secrecy,
and so on. So, Perestroika and Glasnost
was about, you know, openness, but it
was about transparency. It's about It
was about owning up to your mistakes. It
It was about the government taking
responsibility for some things that it
should not have done, that sort of
thing. But it came at a time when the
when the standards in the USSR were
declining significantly.
The decline of the standards in the USSR
began with the death of Joseph Stalin.
Then you have Nikita Khrushchev, and
then you have, you know,
a slow gradual decline in standards in
the USSR. More and more
bureaucratization of the of of the
Politburo and the entire nation, more
corruption, less emphasis on
cutting-edge technologies. The USSR
starts going behind in the computing
race. Eventually, by the 1980s, it's
like 10-15 years behind the US in
supercomputing, in computing overall.
And
after
uh after the 1970s, it it's it gives up
on the space race.
And um
you know, the standards in the nuclear
reactors decline. So, it was a slow
gradual decline of standards,
setting it off setting it off rust and
rot in the entire system.
And that's when Gorbachev decided to
bring in Perestroika and Glasnost.
So, people who had lived through the
'50s and '60s, in the 1980s, they could
see that things had declined
significantly. And the nation's morale
was already down because of all that.
And then you bring in Perestroika and
Glasnost, which reveals even more
cock-ups, let's say.
And that again
contributes to further decline in
not standard, but morale.
You know, all people stopped believing
in their government.
People became
>> [clears throat]
>> dejected.
So, it it to some extent contributed
>> [clears throat]
>> to the further decline of the USSR.
But overall, the
the the the disintegration of the USSR,
it had multiple reasons. It was One of
the factors was, you could say,
Perestroika and Glasnost. The bigger
factor was a decline in standards that
happened as a as a creeping decline year
after year, decade after decade.
And also because of the encirclement of
the USSR by the Anglo-Saxon Empire.
The Anglo-Saxon Empire controlled much
of the global economy. They controlled
the trade routes, the oceans, and they
had encircled the USSR.
And
the USSR its its economy wasn't doing
great. And overall, all these factors
together came together to
And because of the weak leadership of
Mikhail Gorbachev, also. Because of
which the too much freedom was given to
the
to the various SSRs.
And all of that eventually led to the
collapse of the USSR.
VSVS says, "Was the Indus Valley
Civilization truly a civilization by
modern definitions, or was it just the
westernmost branch of a larger far old
far older Vedic civilization whose
records were systematically wiped out to
create the Aryan invasion myth?"
Like I've said,
I don't several dozen times.
>> [clears throat]
>> I'm sure you've not seen it, so I'm not
It's not a criticism.
But like I've said so many times,
calling
this
this entity
a distinct civilization is one of the
biggest lies that has been foisted upon
the people of India.
These days, there is a tendency to to to
to name
or to call every new archaeological
discovery as a new civilization. Kiladi
civilization, that civilization, this
civilization. Every new archaeological
discovery is apparently a new
civilization now.
That's how the idiotic media reports
things.
India's media is is the lowest standard
in the world, whether it is in
geopolitics or it is in whether it's in
history or whatever. Lowest standards.
So,
and our historians also have have
contributed They have done the biggest
damage by calling this a separate
civilization, Indus Valley Civilization,
Harappan Civilization.
It's not a separate distinct
civilization.
It is
a period of time in our civilizational
history.
It was not isolated and separated and
existed in in in in in isolation in the
west of India.
It was connected to the rest of India.
And you can see the connections all over
the place, even all the way down south,
where you have the same kind of script
with with some other characters in in
places like Tamil Nadu.
The Like look today, look at India
today.
We have north, west, east, south south
east, north
north, south, east, west of India,
right? Very large subcontinent.
And it's all interconnected. You go to
Assam, you will see a certain script,
certain kind of culture.
You go to Tamil Nadu, you go to Kerala,
you will see something totally
different. You go to Kashmir, you go to
Ladakh, you go to Haryana, Punjab,
totally different kind of culture.
Apparently, superficially, it will be
very different.
Go to western India, Gujarat, Kutch,
Sindh, Balochistan, very different
culture once again, apparently.
But all interconnected. All part of a of
a greater whole that is just one
overall thing. Similarly,
during the Saraswati Sindhu time, you
had the same thing. India was
interconnected.
It was not isolated. It was not a
separate civilization.
So, the Indus Valley phase, the Harappan
phase, or the Saraswati Sindhu phase is
just one
period of our history. It is our
history.
We are the continuation
of the same thing, of the so-called
Indus Valley Civilization. It never
disappeared. It never died out. It
continued, and here we are. We are part
of that. All right?
Okay, now I have 27 super chats. It's
never going to end.
All right, let me see. What next do we
have?
Okay, I'm going to take questions for
maybe 10 minutes more, cuz I can't take
them forever.
Um VSVS says, "Grim
Grivok is Kanglu Mia from Superpower
Bangladesh." I have no idea what that
means. Who is Grim Grivok?
Who is Grim Grivok?
Um
I have no idea who's Grim Grivok, but
okay, thank you for letting me know,
sir.
Thank you.
Um
"Whose side should a man take if there's
a clash between his mom and wife? Why
should an you know, innocent man do in
the side of type of situation?" Listen,
this is a geo This is a history episode.
I have no idea about clash between mom
and wife.
Uh maybe I'm not the right person to ask
this question. All right, sir. And
anyway, today I'm discussing history.
>> [clears throat]
>> James Our friend James is back. "Look at
Manali, HP towns in Himachal Pradesh
towns. They're becoming more unplanned
and congested. Alpine towns thrive,
beautiful. No wonder all good
civilizations run in the west.
Um the problem in many of these towns
in
various parts of India.
One of the major problems is the
large-scale infiltration
and settlement of uh
Bangladeshi, Rohingya, etc.
infiltrators.
Now what how is this being done? What is
the modus operandi? What are the
logistical things they're doing? Who all
is is complicit in this at local scale,
at larger scale? I will not go into
that.
But one of the major problems why towns
even in beautiful parts of India like
Himachal Pradesh etc. are getting
becoming unlivable
is because
of this in in illegal infiltration. The
settlement of illegal infiltrators in in
all these places.
20 years ago there was no in no
Bangladeshis etc. in these places. Now
it's they're all over the place.
And clearly the government
at the local level, at the central level
would know about this. So I'm not sure
what is happening, why it's happening.
And these are some of the reasons why
you have all [clears throat] these
problems that are that are
present.
And you know what?
To
make a town or a city livable
takes effort.
And for that to happen you need people
who are
who are genuinely invested in making the
country better and making
the city or the town better.
But typically you don't have that in
India.
These are the reasons why you have all
these issues in India.
And what are the root causes of that?
It's it goes back to the British
occupation era and the kind of mess they
left behind.
But yeah, let's not go that's too much
of a long discussion to have right now.
But anyway, James, thank you for
pointing this out, sir.
Did I watch Tondar? I haven't watched it
yet. I haven't watched it yet and I look
forward to watching it in the next
couple of days. I just need to find some
time. It's a pretty long movie.
I need to find like three, four hours
somewhere that I can go and watch it.
Maybe I'll do it in the next couple of
days.
I definitely I'm going to watch it.
VSVS says James need to be needs to be
humble. Well, James, I in my opinion is
a good guy.
I appreciate James. He
brings out interesting uh things to
discuss, asks interesting questions in
his own
unique way. So
yeah, I appreciate James.
Amisha says, "When did the sexualization
of female breasts begin?
Is the objectification of the female
form purely sociological or is it baked
into the human species?"
When did the sexualization of female
breasts begin?
I think this nonsense comes from
Look, um I'm not sure.
I mean, if you look at Indian um
sculptures from the pre-occupation era
almost every female form
female sculpture
is depicted bare bare-chested,
bare-breasted.
So clearly it was not something that was
taboo and it was not something that was
so that was sexualized.
Right? In India at least.
>> [clears throat]
>> It looks like based on the the the the
sculptures and carvings that are all
over the subcontinent from before the
occupation era like like before 1000 AD
it's like
prevalent everywhere that females had
their chests uncovered and there there
was nothing taboo or sexual about it.
So when did this start? I suppose
it may have started with um
I'm not really sure. [laughter]
When did the
when did females start to have
have to start covering up in India? That
obviously starts with the uh
you know, the the gradual creeping
Turkic occupation of India with their
foreign culture which regarded uncovered
women as pieces of meat. That we know,
but when did the sexualization of female
breasts start? I'm not really sure.
I haven't really thought about that and
um
is it purely sociological? Is it baked
in the human species?
Um some of it may to some extent be
baked into human species.
Is it social Some of it may be so maybe
it's it's a combination of the two
factors.
But it's not something I've given much
thought to so I don't really have
maybe the best answer to this. Sorry
about that.
Okay.
Um VSVS says what Amisha is asking began
mainly after the Victorian era. This was
never an issue in ancient India before
the invasions. The sexualization of the
female form, all that. Uh definitely.
No.
It it
the the the requirement to cover up the
female body, I think it it started with
the creeping Turkic occupation of India.
And obviously the Victorian era morals
were like it was
very similar to the Arabic morals,
right? Women have to be completely
modest, covered. Not a single um
>> [snorts]
>> inch of skin should be visible apart
from the face, you know, your hands have
to be covered by gloves. Even showing
ankles is is naughty and that sort of
nonsense, right?
So yeah.
So it was like you say, it was never an
issue in ancient India before the
foreign occupation of India.
Right, VSVS. Um
VSVS gifted 10 memberships. Well, that
is very kind of you, sir. Very kind of
you. Thank you very much.
Ankita Kachhap Ankitaji has gifted 10
memberships. Thank you so much, ma'am. I
really appreciate you. Thank you.
VSVS has give gifted 50 memberships.
Good lord, good gods.
Thank you very much, sir. That's really
indeed very kind of you and very
helpful.
Um you're helping a lot of people. Thank
you so much.
Jagjit Singh is a new member. Thank you
very much, Jagjit Singhji, and welcome
to the membership of this channel. Thank
you very much.
My uh
Su- Sugandh says, "My opinion on Palki
Sharma." Look,
I don't express opinions about private
people. Not public people. I will have
opinions about people that matter at a
global scale. Maybe Donald Trump.
Definitely Donald Trump, definitely
Narendra Modi, definitely Vladimir
Putin, definitely Xi Jinping, definitely
Elon Musk, Steve Jobs, historical
figures, etc. I speak about these people
that genuinely matter at the global
level, people who are genuinely
impactful.
Uh I do not comment about other people.
There's no point.
Otherwise this becomes a gossip channel,
right? What do I think of this person?
Should I criticize that person?
I I'm not going to do that. All right?
But anyway, thank you for the question.
And Abhinav Singh has gifted 20
memberships. Well, thank you so much all
of you and including you, sir. Abhinav
Singhji, thank you so much.
Um
Bijou Saikia says, "In the past being
atheistic was
being an atheist was was punishable
offense in Christianity. Then how today
so many Europeans have become atheists?"
Because Christianity has lost ground
significantly
in Europe. Christianity is
the majority of Europeans have given up
on Christianity.
They probably have seen through
what Christianity really is.
And because of
the effects of what the Europeans call
the Enlightenment, Enlightenment
and the effects of the French Revolution
and the ripple effect it has had on
large-scale European society, there's
been a
you know, the introduction of what the
French called laïcité.
What in the west is called secularism,
which is different from Indian
secularism. In Indian secularism in
India secularism means Hinduphobia.
In Europe secularism means the
separation of church and state. Which
means the church no longer is the
authority to issue laws and you know,
um influence the state or control the
state.
Which
was the main source of power the church
had. So once that happened the church
became kind of powerless and that's how
people just walked away from the church,
from Christianity. And
that's how it happened.
Uh is very naughty name. Yes. Is not is
very bad. Is very bad. What was the TFR
like in the ancient world? I'm not sure,
man. I'm not sure what the TFR was like
in the ancient world. I've not studied
TFR data from the ancient world so I
can't say.
Um it would have been different at
different points in time. There were
times when there were population
bottlenecks on the planet and when you
only had apparently a few thousand
humans who survived. Maybe during the
the aftermath of the Toba supervolcano
eruption.
Indians in India Indians did survive,
but apparently there was a population
bottleneck and so on.
>> [clears throat]
>> So when you have such bottleneck events
and you have the founder effect etc. the
TFR is very low for a while.
For maybe a few decades etc. And there
were times, you know, for the longest
time the population of the world was
just just a few millions.
It is estimated uh that during the peak
of the
Saraswati Sindhu phase of our history
the population in northern western India
total combined was about 5 million
possibly.
5 million. It's 50 lakhs.
As you can see the TFR would have been
good but the overall population was very
low. So it depends and I don't really
have the statistics, the data, the
figures.
Can't say, but it has varied at
different points in time in history.
Okay, VSVS has again gifted 10
memberships. Thank you. Thank you so
much.
And everybody also thank
whoever is received the membership I'm
sure is very grateful to you, sir.
Uh Bijou Saikia says, "I was reading an
article by an expert who predicted that
in the coming years Hindi will become
more and more Sanskritized and most of
the Persian words, phrases will be
replaced by English.
What's my view? I have no idea.
Will Hindi become more Sanskritized? I
think
you have
you know, an increasing intro-gression
of English
vocabulary into Indian parlance.
I just used a French word here, but uh
see
>> [clears throat]
>> people now regularly use English English
words and expressions in
their conversations in Indian languages.
So, I'm not sure about Sanskritization.
I think there's more and more adoption
of English or whatever.
I don't think it's a very healthy thing
and I have nothing against
Sanskritization. I think I would I would
very much welcome it. I would welcome
the purification of the Hindi language.
I have no issue with Persian Persian
language also, but my point is we should
use our own languages.
Will this happen? I don't know for sure.
If this happens, I'll be very happy with
it. I will welcome it.
Uh but replacing Persian words with
English,
I would actually want to stick with
Persian more than English.
Uh
Ideally, we should
Sanskritize rather than
you know, have English words coming in.
But will this happen? Will it not
happen? I can't predict the future.
Can't say really.
Mm
Okay, so I will not
What are some blunders of the of modern
India 1947 to present? Look, there are
millions of blunders. One of the
blunders is the partition of India. The
second blunder is
um not accepting, you know,
the accession of various provinces back
into India. The repudiation of Khan
Abdul Ghaffar Khan who wanted
Afghanistan to
to remain united with India.
The giving up of various territories
which should have been ours.
>> [clears throat]
>> Um you know, rejecting
multiple offers for a permanent seat on
the seat on the UN Security Council. I
can, you know, not nuclearizing after
1974 when we tested a nuclear weapon and
so much more.
The blunders go on and on and on.
Right?
Allowing Pakistan to become a nuclear
weapon state state. I could do a
three-hour session on blunders,
actually.
Uh
Suganth says, "You are my geopolitical
guru. Much appreciation from Tamil Nadu.
Thank you very much. Thank you very
much, sir."
Lot of evidence is that shows that Tamil
was subordinate to Sanskrit in What's my
opinion? Thank you very much. What's my
opinion? This is a super controversial
topic. Whichever answer I give you, I
will get lot of flak and backlash.
Um Look, if you look at
the his- this the history of Tamil Nadu,
the Sangam period, etc. It It's said to
go back 10,000 years.
And if you look at the archaeological
evidence that we have off the coast of
Tamil Nadu,
we have submerged cities that are now
known to exist
like
a hundred 150 m below the sea level.
And those cities would only have been
above sea level like 10,000 years ago.
But does it mean that 10,000 years ago
people in this region spoke Tamil?
Or was it proto-Tamil? Was it some other
language? We don't know for sure.
Was Tamil subordinate to subordinate to
Sanskrit?
>> [clears throat]
>> I don't know about subordinate. We know
for a fact, look,
that the Chola kings
used Sanskrit.
No question about it.
The Cholas claimed descent from the
Suryavanshi dynasty, the Ikshvaku
dynasty.
The Cholas were Shaivites.
The The Cholas were unapologetic Hindus,
right?
And they used Sanskrit. They They
brought Sanskrit to various parts of
Southeast Asia.
So, even for the Cholas who were native
Tamil speakers, they regarded Sanskrit
as the
civilizational language.
So,
if you can regard that as evidence
that Sanskrit was regarded as a higher
language by the greatest of the Tamil
emperors, then I think it does stand.
But look, I'm not I don't want to get
into this battle of which is better,
which is superior, which is higher,
which is lower.
I think we need to go beyond these
battles and all these petty fights, you
know? The world wants us to keep
fighting each other.
We should Instead of fighting each
other, we should unite.
>> [clears throat]
>> I'm sure all the languages of India have
very ancient lineages
and uh
what we know for sure is that Sanskrit,
you know, was the language of the
Saraswati Sindhu phase of our history,
the Indus script,
if you can call it that, does encode
Sanskrit. It can also encode any other
language if you want to, but
Yeah, so it's a complicated topic. My
point is we should cherish all of our
languages, Sanskrit as well as Tamil, as
well as all the other
great languages of India.
And we should instead of fighting, unite
and take the country forward.
And that brings me to the end
of today's
uh super chats and live stream.
It is Look, now Vladimir Putin wants me
wants my opinion on somebody else. Like
I said Like I said, I don't express
opinion on ordinary people like like me
or
I only
express an opinion about people who have
a global impact
at a global scale on the world.
If I start expressing my opinion about
this person, that YouTuber, this news
reader,
etc., then this becomes a gossip channel
and that's not my intention ever. All
right?
And we have one more super chat.
VSBS says question by Neeraj Desai, "If
Ashoka converted to Buddhism, how come
his mention is Devanampriya,
which is contradictory to Buddhist
beliefs that God don't exist?"
>> [clears throat]
>> Good question.
Okay, this will be the final question of
the day. After that, if there's any more
super chat, I will not be able to take
it because I've already reached almost 3
hours.
So,
uh
it is said that Ashoka converted to
Buddhism. First of all, in Dharmic
paths, there is no conversion.
Okay?
You decide to start walking this path,
that is your choice, but you don't have
to convert for that. But now it is said
that Ashoka converted to Buddhism.
That's what our history books tell us.
Converted. They use the word conversion.
So, if Ashoka converted to Buddhism, he
became a Buddhist, then why does he
refer to himself as Devanampriya,
Priyadarshi,
in his inscriptions almost everywhere?
Devanampriya means the beloved of the
gods.
Now, if you're a Buddhist, how can you
say that you are the beloved of the
gods?
Because apparently, according to
Buddhist belief,
God don't exist doesn't exist. Well,
please understand this. Today we look at
Buddhism in a certain way.
But according to what is called
Buddhism,
Buddhism doesn't say that gods don't
exist.
Buddhism said says that gods are
impermanent.
That's what Buddhism says.
But that is the opinion of the Buddhist
path of Dharma. We have so many
different paths of Dharma.
Dharmic paths. You have Charvaka which
says that nothing exists. The only word
is the is the world that you see. There
is no
soul, there is no Atman, there is no
God, whatever. So, there is also a valid
path in Dharma.
So, according to the Buddha path,
gods exist, but they are not permanent.
They are impermanent.
So, Ashoka was pushing Buddhism on the
country, on the civilization, right?
And he wanted to rule a huge population
which had lots of people who belong to
various different
Dharmic paths.
And to rule them all, you have to be the
ruler of them all by
essentially keeping them all happy.
So, you call yourself Devanampriya
Priyadarshi, the beloved of all the
gods.
That works and it is not contrary to
Buddhism.
Okay, that brings me to the actual end
of this live stream. Thank you very
much, everybody. It's been almost 3
hours. It has been fun. I enjoyed this.
Took a lot of very interesting
questions, including the super chats and
and I would like to thank everybody who
has
uh donated memberships to various
people. Thank you so much. It's very
kind of you.
And uh So, all right. That brings me to
the end of today's live stream. Thank
you very much for the questions. Keep
asking questions. Keep
Keep Keep Keep Keep raising your
standards.
And I look forward to seeing you in
tomorrow's live stream, which is going
to be an ask me anything. You can ask me
anything on the super chat.
Look forward to seeing you there. Take
care.
I'll see you
tomorrow.